<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The riches of grace displayed: the second part. In the great instances thereof. In giving the son. Sending the spirit. Effectual calling. God's covenanting with man. By W. Bagshaw, minister of the gospel</title>
            <author>Bagshawe, William, 1628-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 218 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 107 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77300</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B433BA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230488</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899619</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899619</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154105</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77300)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154105)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2397:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The riches of grace displayed: the second part. In the great instances thereof. In giving the son. Sending the spirit. Effectual calling. God's covenanting with man. By W. Bagshaw, minister of the gospel</title>
                  <author>Bagshawe, William, 1628-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 208 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Ralph Shelmardine in Manchester,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Grace (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154105:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154105:1"/>
            <p>THE RICHES OF GRACE DISPLAYED: The SECOND PART. In the great Inſtances thereof.
<list>
                  <item>In giving the Son.</item>
                  <item>Sending the Spirit.</item>
                  <item>Effectual Calling.</item>
                  <item>God's Covenanting with Man.</item>
               </list> By <hi>W. Bagſhaw,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ralph Shelmardine</hi> in <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:154105:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154105:2"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou maiſt take notice, That the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Author of this Book did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to Publiſh ſomething on this Excellent Subject, in a Book Entituled, <hi>The Riches of Grace Diſplayed,</hi> &amp;c. in the Year <hi>1674.</hi> To which this is a Second Part, proceeding on ſeveral great Inſtances to the fifth in number, which are mentioned in the Title page: To which will be added a Third Part, of five Inſtances more of the ſame <hi>Rich Grace,</hi> to wit, of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's <hi>Juſtifying, Adopting, Sanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Comforting,</hi> and <hi>Glorifying</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. The Subject is of the higheſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern; and this may be ſaid of the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of it, That it is <hi>fully,</hi> and yet <hi>briefly</hi> done. And the Reader may be aſſured, that as the price cannot be great, ſo he ſhall not pay for ſcarce a ſuperfluous word in the whole. May God Bleſs it to the eternal Advantage of every careful peruſer of it. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:154105:3"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. line 1. read <hi>manner.</hi> p. 4. l. 21. dele <hi>which is.</hi> p. 5. in the Marg. r. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendabilem. ib. Polus.</hi> p. 14. l. 7. r. <hi>at. Ibid.</hi> l. 23. dele <hi>ſay.</hi> p 17. l. 16. r. <hi>O that.</hi> p. 25. l. 12. dele <hi>he came ſo.</hi> p. 30. l. 13. r. <hi>inflicted.</hi> p. 31. l. 19. r. <hi>O that.</hi> p. <hi>Ib.</hi> l. 22. r. <hi>pledge.</hi> p. 48. l. 10. r. <hi>know.</hi> p. 55. l. 10. r. <hi>cures.</hi> p. 63. l. 14. r. <hi>yet.</hi> p. 64. in the Marg. r. <hi>rependere.</hi> p. 70. l. 11. r. <hi>deſires.</hi> p. 72. l. 14. r. <hi>her.</hi> p. 76. l. 18. add <hi>is.</hi> p. 81. Marg. r. <hi>againſt 'em.</hi> p. 87. l. 5. r. <hi>and.</hi> p. 103. l. 13. r. <hi>do.</hi> p. 110. l. 22. add <hi>is.</hi> p. 122. l. 6. r. <hi>living water.</hi> p. 133. Marg. r. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 143. l. 16. r. <hi>chearing.</hi> p. 147. l. 4. r. <hi>of us all.</hi> p. 154. l. 20. r. <hi>and deſign.</hi> p. 164. Marg. r. <hi>malè colorata.</hi> p. 180. l. 15. r. <hi>Context.</hi> p. 182. l. 25. r. <hi>this.</hi> p. 184. l. 2. r. <hi>removed.</hi> p. 187. l. 1. add <hi>as well.</hi> p. 193. l. 12. r. <hi>crys:</hi> p. 203. Marg. r. <hi>Date.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154105:3"/>
            <head>THE RICHES OF GRACE. The SECOND PART.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 John 4.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Herein is Love, not that we Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved God, but that He Loved us, and ſent His Son to be a Propitiation for our Sins.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>DId not Divine <hi>John</hi> carry <hi>Grace</hi> and Love in his Heart as well as in his Name?
<note place="margin">BP Brown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrigg.</note> It was well obſerved by one of great
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154105:4"/>eminency, (and is worthy of the obſervation of others) that as he ſhared above others in the Love of his Saviour, he (above others) ſhewed (as well as bare) Love to his Saviour.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jo.</hi> 13.23.</note> As he was the Diſciple that <hi>Jeſus</hi> Loved,
<note place="margin">He was a compound of Love and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> he was the Diſciple by whom <hi>Jeſus</hi> was beloved; and in the exerciſe of Love, his fellowſhip was with the Father,
<note place="margin">See Doctor Roberts.</note> as well as with the Son <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Witneſs this Epiſtle,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Ja.</hi> 1.3.</note> and that part of it wherein my Text ſtands. And he who felt ſuch pure flames in his own breaſt, was deſirous to kindle the like in the breaſts of others; thence doth he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play the Love of God before 'em; His heart would not (eaſily) off from that Subject; and it kept his Pen to (and on) it. On that ſweet ſtring he ſtruck in the Verſe before this, and on it, he ſtrikes again in this Verſe, wherein,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Matter treated of is Love, Love in its height.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:154105:4"/>
            <p n="2">2. The Matter of his treating thereon is, (as was uſual with him,)</p>
            <p n="1">1. Negatively, the excellency of Love lay not in Mens Love to God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Poſitively, it lyes in Gods Love to Men. Of whoſe Love, there is an eminent inſtance, to wit, ſending <hi>His Son to be a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for our Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Text hath in it fair footing for ſundry points or obſervations; but it falls for my preſent deſign, to touch only on this Doctrine.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſending of His Son to be a Propitiation for Mens Sins, was an eminent evidence of the <hi>Rich Grace</hi> and free Love of God the Father.</p>
            <p>Of this perſon's Love doth the Text and Context much treat. That we are to take the word God therein perſonally for the Father, is argued from his being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from the Son, and having that action which is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154105:5"/>eſpecially appropiated to the Father,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Differentia eſt per pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pria &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriata. Bp. Prid. manuduct. p.</hi> 34.</note> aſcribed to him, that is, ſending the Son. Though there be no inequality among the Divine Perſons (or Subſiſtents) there is an order, and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaks of the firſt Perſon,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53.10.</note> as the firſt propounder (and mover) as to the work of Mans redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And when the Text ſaith <hi>herein is Love,</hi> or in this is Love, it ſpeaks as much as I have put into my Doctrine.
<note place="margin">See the Eng. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not.</note> I find it thus gloſſed on, <hi>The very nature of Love doth herein appear:</hi> One (I remember) expreſſed himſelf thus, <hi>This is Love worth pointing at;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> S. E.</note> what if I ſay, this is Love worth wondring at? it is much on this ſcore eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that God the Father is ſtiled Love,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Jo.</hi> 4.8.16.</note> which is full of Love, Love it ſelf.</p>
            <p>And in the foregoing Verſe, it is ſaid expreſly, In this was the Love of God manifeſted, in this mainly,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> though not in this only; in this above, and not only among
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154105:5"/>other things, that he gave his <hi>only Begotten Son:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.16.</note> So God Loved the World ſo wonderfully, ſo as cannot be (to the full) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed or conceived.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Here is a</hi> Sic <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a</hi> Sicut.</note> So that good Men and Angels are fill'd with admiration. This Love had no preſident,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8.</note> and ſhall have no parallel.
<note place="margin">Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile reddit ſalus ad lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> This commendeth (or rendreth commendable) the Love of God the Father particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly.</p>
            <p>That we may take a fairer view of this his Love, we will offer at the reſolution of certain Queſtions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Who is it that thus declares his Love?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it not God the Father? Did not the Son come (and was he not ſent) out of His Boſome?
<note place="margin">Vide Amy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raldi Theſ. de peccato in Spirit. Sanctum.</note> Now, did not Mans Sin in viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Law (and firſt Covenant) ſtrike very fully at this Perſon, from whom (if we regard the order of the Perſons in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head) that Law and Covenant
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154105:6"/>had the firſt riſe? Had not He been what He is, if Man had never been? And could not He have Glorified Himſelf in Mans Damnation?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5 8.</note> Now, that He againſt whom Man had Sinn'd, ſhould for Man provide a Saviour; that he who was provoked by the World, ſhould ſend his Son for, as well as into the World; that he that is All-bleſſed, ſhould beſtow on provokers this prime Bleſſing, that he who could have honoured His juſtice ſhould thus declare His mercy: Is not this wondrous mercy?</p>
            <p>The Second queſtion is, <hi>Whom did God the Father ſend?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was it not His Son? and as is elſewere expreſſed,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32.</note> His own Son, as the verſe before the Text hath it,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Jo.</hi> 4.9.</note> 
               <hi>His only Begotten Son?</hi> Had He ſent a Servant, there had been <hi>Grace</hi> in the buſineſs; there had ſtill been more, had He ſent one of thoſe Men that are his Sons by the <hi>Grace</hi> of Adoption; or one
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154105:6"/>of thoſe chief Sons by Creation, the Angels. But His ſending His proper Son, His Son begotten in a way beyond our expreſſion,
<note place="margin">Modo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effabili.</note> (or conception) not one Begotten Son of many, (and yet we find thoſe that have many, loth to part with one) but an only Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son, a Son of the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual Eſſence with himſelf,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.30.</note> a Son that from Eternity <hi>was with Him,</hi> and <hi>was His delight,</hi> His dear Son,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.13. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> (or the Son of His Love) this is Grace to a wonder; and they that are made partakers of the ſaving benefit thereof cannot but wonder at it.</p>
            <p>The Third queſtion is, <hi>What is implyed in Gods act of ſending?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. This Phraſe muſt not have a force put on it.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.6.7.</note> It doth not imply that the Son as God is at all inferiour to His Father.
<note place="margin">Miſſio non tollit aequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem.</note> Among Men, one may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by and from others that are His equals. Nor doth it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, that the Son was at all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154105:7"/>averſe to the work he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took, His heart was in't.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But it denoteth a decree and purpoſe (of the Father thus to imploy His Son) which was from Eternity; and withall, that the Son as Mediator, was by the Father Commiſſion'd to His work; and we find the Scripture laying no little ſtreſs as on the work of the Son,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.10.</note> ſo on the Will of His Father. We may not well ſuppoſe, that the Son would come and become a Sufferer, without the conſent of His Father: If He could have done ſo, would it have been of avail to Mans Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation? He that came freely was authorized fully. Now that He ſhould give him ſuch a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion as it were under Seal (the Scripture ſpeaks of <hi>Sealing him;</hi>)
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Je.</hi> 6.27.</note> If alſo we conſider, that it is ſaid elſewhere, and juſt before my Text,
<note place="margin">Dedit non vendidit, dedit, haud conceſſit.</note> that <hi>He gave him freely</hi> (for what's freer than gift?) He gave Him, and ſold Him not, he gave
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154105:7"/>Him and granted him not; when Men were ſo far from deſerving, that they could not deſire Him; we have all reaſon to cry <hi>Grace! Grace!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's next enquired, <hi>Whither did God the Father ſend His Son?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was it not into the World,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jo.</hi> 1.14.</note> the poliuted World,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 5.19.</note> the World that lay in evil as a Carcaſe lyes in its filth;
<note place="margin">Sub po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtate mali.</note> a World where he was to meet with the groſſeſt abuſes, to be dealt with as if he had not been worthy of it?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jo.</hi> 15.18.</note> A Prince's coming from a Palace to a Dunghill, was as nothing to this Condeſcenſion and <hi>Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fifth Queſtion is, <hi>For whom did God the Father ſend His Son into the World?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was it not for us? for the ſake of ſuch as we are?</p>
            <p n="1">1. It was for us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.</note> and not for fallen Angels, Chriſt took not on Him the nature of Angels, He took not them by the hand,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> nor was ſent ſo to do. The Angels that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154105:8"/>fell, Sinn'd without a Tempter, and they periſh without the tender of a Saviour. I am aware, that beſides what is hinted in the laſt ſentence, there are by ſome of the Learned ſome reaſons (or congruities) produc'd, why God ſhould rather paſs by fallen Angels than fallen Man; but I fall fully in with ſuch as would have Man to attribute this chiefly to His Will;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>So Mr.</hi> Hopkins.</note> (and good Will towards him.) He may think that if Angels had been Redeemed, they would have been larger Veſſels of Honour; and did not Man Sin upon a ſmall (and for ought we know the firſt) Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Again, If we be from our hearts devoted to the Lord, it was for us more than for other Men, that the Son of God was ſent. Though there be in Him (and in His Death) a ſufficiency for all the World,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 5.8.9.</note> (yea for a Thouſand Worlds) yet the efficacy of His ſuffering, (and ſo of His Fathers
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154105:8"/>ſending) is peculiar to the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Can we refrain ſpeaking of God's <hi>Grace,</hi> as exceeding Rich, when we ſee him preferring us above Angels, and many Men that are round about us?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.10.</note> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when having conſidered our ſelves comparatively, we conſider,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2.3.</note> that abſolutely we are 1. Undeſerving, leſs than the leaſt mercy, and yet the objects of this greateſt mercy; and 2. Ill-deſerving, that he ſhould ſend His Son to redeem us, that might have ſent His Wrath to conſume us; we are delivered that might have been deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>The laſt queſtion, which will call for the largeſt Anſwer is, <hi>For what end (or on what Errand) was Chriſt ſent into the World?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> One main End (and Errand) is laid down in the Text, which whoſoever well weighs, will cry out, <hi>Behold what manner of Love the Father hath beſtowed on us, He was ſent to be a Propitiation for our ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:154105:9"/>
            <p>We'll firſt conſider the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the word <hi>Propitiation.</hi> And it is not doubted, but in it is a reſpect and alluſion to ſuch <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory</hi> Sacrifices as were uſed and appointed in the time of the Law.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Dr.</hi> Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> Crellius.</note> As there were gratulatory Offerings, wherein the Offerers teſtified their Love to God, with their thankfullneſs for his favours: So there were Expiatory Offerings, which tended to appeaſe God, and apply the pardon of Sin to Men, and thoſe were all of them Bloody ones; without ſhedding of Blood there is no Remiſſion, ſaid the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>Accordingly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb</hi> 9.22.</note> Chriſt's being a <hi>Propitiation,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Implyes His being a ſufferer, and that unto Death.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His being ſubſtituted in the room,
<note place="margin">Idem</note> and ſo ſuffering not only for the good, but withall in the ſtead of Sinners; as the Sacrifices were ſlain, to prevent their being ſo that brought 'em.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:154105:9"/>
            <p n="3">3. His ſo far anſwering and ſatisfying God His Father, and making a Compenſation for the wrong done to His Law and juſtice, that on the ſcore thereof, He is attoned, and <hi>Propitious</hi> and <hi>Gracious</hi> to believing Penitents. He is their Peace,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.14.</note> the procurer and effecter thereof; what the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Sacrifices were in type, He is in truth.</p>
            <p>I will not conceal, that ſuch as are eminently judicious do judg,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Truemans <hi>great</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation.</note> that in the word <hi>Propitiation</hi> there is an eye to the Mercy-Seat, or cover of the Ark, that Holy of Holy's; and queſtionleſs, Chriſt is in ſubſtance what that was in ſignification, and its ſaid, He is called by the Name of His own Type.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That, as to the matter of it was of pure Gold; He is much more excellent (and laſting) than that.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That in its uſe ſerved to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe betwixt Mens ſight and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154105:10"/>the Law of God which was in the Ark, Chriſt interpoſeth betwixt Chriſtians and the Law, as condemning, and procures that His Father doth not look on and judg them according to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I add,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sculte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus <hi>on the</hi> Romans.</note> As the Ark (or between the Cherubims, that were at the ends thereof) God did commune and meet with His people;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.</note> In (and through) Chriſt it is, that they and He meet and maintain Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now we will make a little ſearch, how Chriſt is ſaid to be a Propitiation for our Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is noted,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1.2.</note> that the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word Tranſlated <hi>Propitiation,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noteth covering; and no doubt Chriſt doth cover our Sins from the avenging eye of God.</p>
            <p>But we will in our anſwer moſt regard the <hi>Propitiaton Offerings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Say,</hi> 1. They are not to be hear kened to, nor patiently heard
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:154105:10"/>who ſay,
<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Non me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rita ſed &amp; peccata duxerunt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>See Biſh.</hi> Brown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrigg <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. pag. (mibi)</hi> 177. Ro. 6. <hi>laſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> that ſome did procure ſo as to deſerve this <hi>Propitiation;</hi> all having Sinn'd deſerve puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, even that that is everlaſting.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our Sins made ſuch a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory</hi> Sacrifice as Chriſt offered (and was) needful. Had not He been Sacrificed, we muſt have been Sacrifices to Divine wrath.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Lord who laid our Sins (in reſpect of the puniſhment due for 'em) upon Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53.6.</note> upon His account taketh off the guilt of our Sins, and deals with us as to our Eternal ſtate, as if we had not Sinn'd.</p>
            <p>It may be ask'd, <hi>Is not Chriſt a Propitiation for our Souls?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, <hi>He is ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This obſervation appears weighty; the Phyſician healeth both his Patient and his Diſeaſe; the latter by removing it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> S. R. <hi>on the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi>
               </note> the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer by recovering him. Chriſt is a <hi>Propitiation,</hi> both as to our Souls and as to our Sins; our Sins He removes out of the ſight of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154105:11"/>God, our Souls He reſtoreth to the favour of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What if before I make a more formal Application of this point, I lead others in the way of this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bleſſed Lord! thou Father of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt!</hi> How is it, that I who hear ſo much of Thy Son, and of His being made a <hi>Propitiation,</hi> and ſent by Thee for that end, ſo little, ſee thine exceeding Grace therein.</p>
            <p>And (in my meer impure na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalls) am far from having the Bowels of a Child; but what other Father ever had ſuch Bowel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercy's, as thoſe which thou ſheweſt me through thy Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed Son.</p>
            <p>Had He not been a Sacrifice, He had not been a <hi>Propitiation;</hi> I have read, and do believe, that though every Reconciliation doth not, a <hi>Propitiation</hi> doth imply a ſatisfaction made on behalf of Offenders: Undoubtedly, the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154105:11"/>Sufferings of Thy Son were in an Ancient Church well ſtiled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known ones. I cannot Fathom, or take a full Meaſure of the depths into which He Deſcended, when His Soul was made an Offering for Sin.</p>
            <p>But ſure I am, the lower he ſtoops, the better thy Love may by every right Eye be ſeen. Thou waſt pleaſed with His bruiſing, as it had a reference to my binding up. Was ever Love (ſave that of Thy Son, and Spirit one with Thee) like Thine? and that this heavy heart of mine was lifted up to Admiringsat, and Praiſes for it! Through Thy dear Son in whom mercy flows to me, let my Soul aſcend and preſent her Acknowledgments to Thee! May Thy Love be ſhed abroad in mine heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt aſe of this Point ſhall be of (and for) Caution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt Branch is,</hi> Take we heed, leſt we take occaſion from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:154105:12"/>this Doctrine, to think of the Love of God the Son or Holy Spirit, in a way of Diminution, becauſe it preſents the Love of the Father in a way of Exaltation. <hi>The Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. <hi>v. laſt. Rom.</hi> 15.30.</note> 
               <hi>and the Love of the Spirit,</hi> are ſpoken of as eminent, and indeed as infinite. As there isno Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Divine Perſons, ſo there is no Diviſion in their Love to Men, but a diſtinction there is which is to be obſerved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond Branch is,</hi> Beware we, leſt by our looking at this very great inſtance of God the Fathers Love, our eyes and minds be taken off from other E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences thereof. His Love is Written (and ſhould be read) in the Proviſion He makes for us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.19.20.</note> and the direction he gives to us daily. Though the Sun far out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhines the Stars, the Stars are Lights; and though God's ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding His Son, excell other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of His Grace, yet His
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154105:12"/>Grace is ſhewed, and to be ſeen in the lower tokens of it.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> ſaw Divine goodneſs ſpreading <hi>his Table,</hi> and filling his Cup.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The further Application of the Point, ſhall be reduced under Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of Truth, and Rules of Duly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Firſt inference is,</hi> The Love of God (particularly of God the Father) is of an elder Date, then the actual ſending of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> into the World; this doth flow from that,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4.</note> this was in the <hi>fullneſs of time,</hi> that was from Eternity. Though ſome who place the very nature of Love in delight, are leſs willing to grant, that any are beloved till they are Converted; yet my Text joyns with ſundry others that countenance this diſtinction.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Doctor</hi> Roberts <hi>Believers Evidences. p.</hi> 6.</note> There is a Love of benevolence which leads to that of complacence, of well-wiſhing that brings on that of good-liking; Love intended makes way for Love applyed.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:154105:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I the rather inſiſt on this, becauſe,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. This much tends to quicken Perſons to Duty, eſpecially the grand Duty, Love to God. Should not their Love to Him be without end, whoſe Love to them was before times beginning? Love is no little valued for its Antiquity,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 4.19.</note> and no Love of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is in that point to be compared with the Love of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This conduceth greatly to the Comfort of Perſons. The beſt on Earth are apteſt to complain of their unworthineſs, to have the Love of God continued to 'em: Now this is cheering to ſuch as are in their main deſire (and deſign) for the Lord. He that Love 'em when they could have no worthineſs, will not ceaſe to Love 'em, though now they have none. Weakneſſes in time ſhall not make void Love that was from Eternity.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:154105:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second Inference is,</hi> The Doctrine of the <hi>Socinians</hi> is greatly to be diſliked (yea to be deteſted.) Is it not a body of Hereſie?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A. Biſhop</hi> Uſher. <hi>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  </hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowſmith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Have not Divines of the firſt Rank, ranked it with <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metaniſm?</hi> Here I will only point at its contrariety to the great point I am on.?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Do they not deny Chriſt's being ſent <hi>to be a Propitiation for Sin,</hi> when they affirm that <hi>He</hi> neither made Satisfaction to <hi>His</hi> Father by <hi>His</hi> Death, nor intended any ſuch thing?</p>
            <p>Though the Scripture ſpeak of <hi>His</hi> Dying for us, that is,
<note place="margin">Noſtro loco.</note> inſtead of us, and for Sin, when <hi>He</hi> had none of <hi>His</hi> own to dy for, yea for our ſins, that is, to expiate 'em,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6.</note> and take off the guilt of 'em, ſo that <hi>He</hi> is ſtiled a <hi>Ranſome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Mr. Polhill.</hi>
               </note> one that put <hi>His</hi> Soul into the ſtead of ours, yet they aſſign other ends of <hi>His</hi> Dying, and exclude that great end of <hi>His</hi> being a Propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatory Sacrifice, at which my Text points.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:154105:14"/>
            <p n="2">2. And do they not make way, to their denying that Chriſt made ſatisfaction to infinite Juſtice, when they deny <hi>Him</hi> to be an infinite Perſon? They, what in 'em lies, degrade <hi>Him</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive <hi>Him</hi> of the Honour of <hi>His</hi> Deity,
<note place="margin">Officio non Naturâ.</note> when they ſay, <hi>He</hi> is only God by Office and not by Nature. Had <hi>He</hi> not been very God, could <hi>He</hi> have made payment for the debts owing to God? And whilſt they thus detract from the dignity (and death) of the Son, do they not draw a Cloud be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt their Followers and the Love of the Father?</p>
            <p>Had <hi>He</hi> not been <hi>His</hi> Fathers own proper Son, and ſo of one and the ſame Nature with <hi>Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53.10.</note> or had not <hi>His</hi> Death been an Offering for ſin, <hi>His</hi> Father's Love had not broken out in ſuch great Luſtre.</p>
            <p>But if you will believe 'em, one great Motive which moves 'em to deny the ſatisfaction made
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:154105:14"/>by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> is, that the aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this doth directly thwart with the Grace of <hi>His</hi> Father: How (ſay they) can Redemption be of Free-grace, if it be through and for a full purchaſe?</p>
            <p>But doth not this ſet one part of my Text againſt another? and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents that as inconſiſtent with the Fathers Love, that is rightly repreſented as the great proof thereof?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>According to the ſentiments of our choiceſt Writers, I write what followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. It was wondrous Love in God the Father, that <hi>He</hi> would accept ſatisfaction at the hand of a Surety, when <hi>He</hi> might have exacted it at the hand of every ſinner.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Bunsby <hi>on the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator. Mr.</hi> True<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</note> Though the payment made by Chriſt is valuable, yet it was <hi>Rich Grace</hi> that it was not refuſed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It was wondrous Love in God the Father, that this Surety <hi>His</hi> bleſſed Son, was ſo far of <hi>His</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:154105:15"/>own providing, that <hi>He</hi> is ſaid to <hi>ſet Him forth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25.</note> to lay help on <hi>Him.</hi> The Scripture ſpeaks of <hi>Him</hi> as the firſt Motioner of this matter,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai</hi> 53.10.</note> as having the firſt hand at (and in) the Covenant of Suretiſhip and Redemption.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The management of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming work by the hand of God the Son, had the heart of <hi>His</hi> Father going along with every paſſage of it. Its called the pleaſure of the Lord, <hi>His</hi> pleaſure in the Abſtract, that wherewith <hi>He</hi> is exceedingly pleaſed: <hi>He</hi> was pleaſed with putting <hi>His</hi> Son to pain, as it had a reference to the freeing of Sinners from it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is a wondrous Love in God the Father, that <hi>He</hi> that gave <hi>His</hi> Son to obtain Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Sinners, ſends <hi>His</hi> Spirit to apply it to 'em. In a word, Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is not a whit leſs a Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive (or Gift) to us, becauſe it was a purchaſe to Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:154105:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Third Inference is,</hi> It is no wonder that the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is ſo precious to (and prized) by true Believers, well may they count <hi>Him</hi> their Honour. Do not the beſt of 'em moſt mourn,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7.</note> that they do not Love and value <hi>Him</hi> more?
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Grace is ſpoken of as tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent, and it beſpeaks ſuch a character.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>He</hi> came ſo, <hi>He</hi> came freely according as in the Volume (or head of the Book,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.7, 8, 9.</note> it is Written of <hi>Him. He</hi> was under no obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to us, and <hi>His</hi> Father that ſent <hi>Him</hi> did nothing like forcing <hi>Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>He</hi> knew well how coſtly the work of Redemption would be, and was foreſeen coming,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.8.</note> leaping on the Mountains of difficulty that were before <hi>Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>He</hi> alſo underſtood, that not a few would make light of <hi>Him,</hi> and <hi>His</hi> Sons Sufferings; and the beſt would be far from
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:154105:16"/>walking up to, and worthy of <hi>His</hi> Love. And had not <hi>His</hi> Grace been ſo great to us, yet <hi>His</hi> own excellencies had called for the beſt of our affections.</p>
            <p>But at preſent, we will preſent <hi>His</hi> amiableneſs in the Glaſs that is neareſt us.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jo.</hi> 4.10.</note> This Doctrine teacheth us to ſet the higheſt eſteem on <hi>Him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> N. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood <hi>on this.</hi>
               </note> Is <hi>He</hi> not the gift of God the Father? the chief comprehenſive and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighing gift, the gift of <hi>His</hi> Heart as well as <hi>His</hi> hand? the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the ſent and Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſioned one, to make peace between Heaven and Earth, and that by <hi>His</hi> being made a Burnt. Offering and Sacrifice, on the behalf of Sinners. Should not the Son of God's Love be highly beloved?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Fourth Inference is,</hi> Sin may well be called (what it is) <hi>the Evil.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.</note> Surely the Apoſtle hath not wrong'd it, in ſaying that it ſhews it ſelf exceeding
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:154105:16"/>ſinfull, and intimating that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be called by a worſe Name than its own. The evil of ſin is ſeen in other Glaſſes, but in none more clearly than in that of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>That God the Father ſent, and ſet forth <hi>His</hi> Son <hi>to be a Propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Sins,</hi> doth ſpeak and ſet forth the extream evil that is in Sin. The Drowning of the old World,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Doctor</hi> Arrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith.</note> the Burning of <hi>Sodom</hi> are not ſuch full Proofs thereof, as Chriſts being made a <hi>Propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Sacrifice,</hi> for the taking it away is. It was more that <hi>He</hi> who was the God of Nature ſhould ſuffer for it, than if the whole Courſe of Nature had ſuffered.</p>
            <p>I look not on my ſelf as one competent for the determining of that great ſuit that hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended among great Divines, whether it was abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, that Divine Juſtice ſhould receive Satisfaction, that ſo ſinfull Men might receive
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:154105:17"/>Pardon; or in other words, Whether Gods puniſhing ſinners, flow meerly from <hi>His</hi> Will, or from <hi>His</hi> Nature alſo?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vel uno verbo. See</hi> Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons <hi>Orth. Evan. from Cal.</hi>
               </note> Whether <hi>He</hi> might (as ſome have ſaid) have taken it away with a word, or that in order to the removal of it, blood (even the blood of one that as to <hi>His</hi> Perſon was infinite) was to go.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe things (I with ſome confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence) Write.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Holy Scriptures ſpeak expreſsly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6.</note> that God will by no means clear and acquit the Guilty;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.22.</note> 
               <hi>that without ſhedding of Blood, there is no Remiſſion;</hi> and as Sin let in Death, there muſt be the Death of one able to make a Compenſation to God, in order to the taking away ſin;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr. Burgeſs on Juſtif. part</hi> 2.</note> and ſome think it leſs meet to diſpute what God might have done, ſeeing <hi>He</hi> hath told us what <hi>He</hi> will do, and not do.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:154105:17"/>
            <p n="2">2. There are not a few Phraſes found in Scripture,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebbak.</hi> 1.13.</note> that aſcribe the puniſhment of ſin to <hi>His</hi> Nature, and not to <hi>His</hi> Will only, and all are agreed, that God is in <hi>His</hi> Nature an enemy to ſin; <hi>He</hi> is of purer eyes then to behold it, without bearing Witneſs againſt it, it ſhall not dwell with <hi>Him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 1. <hi>laſt. Rarò ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedentem Sceleſtuns deſeruit poena.</hi>
               </note> The very Heathens had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, that ſin draws ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring after it as the Needle doth the Thread; they made account that Offenders were to ſmart.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If we conſider God as a Governour, and ſin as a Crime (and violation of <hi>His</hi> Righteous Law) it ſeems very agreeable to the ends of <hi>His</hi> Government,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the Ark of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. part</hi> 2. <hi>and Doct.</hi> Tuckney<hi>'s determ.</hi>
               </note> and conduceable to the Declaration of the Glory of ſeveral of <hi>His</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes, that <hi>He</hi> ſhould look for ſatisfaction for the injuries and affronts offer'd to <hi>Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet I cannot gain-ſay thoſe who ſay, that Gods puniſhing ſin doth not ſo neceſſarily flow
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:154105:18"/>from <hi>His</hi> Nature, that there is not an order and interpoſition of <hi>His</hi> Will. <hi>He</hi> in the puniſhment doth not act as thoſe natural neceſſary Agents, the Sun in ſhining and the Fire in Burning; for then <hi>He</hi> ſhould puniſh every act (and degree) of ſin, at the firſt, and to the utmoſt, which we ſee <hi>He</hi> doth not; and <hi>His</hi> threatnings (at leaſt ſundry of 'em) ſhew, what might juſtly be inflicted for ſin,
<note place="margin">De jure.</note> not what ſhall be afflicted for it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That they who make light of ſin (which alafs! moſt do!) would open their eyes (O that God would open 'em) that they might ſee God's anger ſmoaking againſt it, as an evil and bitter thing; and that every Sinner muſt inevitably have dyed for ever,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.19.</note> if the Lord of Life had not in Mans nature dyed, (and ſuffer'd) beyond what can be thought) for it.</p>
            <p>I the rather enlarge on this, becauſe none will be ſo wrapt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:154105:18"/>and raviſhed with the Love of God the Father,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Doct.</hi> Goodwin <hi>of Hell, p.</hi> 248.</note> as they who ſee that they deſerved the hotteſt of <hi>His</hi> Indignation, and muſt have endur'd it, had <hi>He</hi> not ſent <hi>His Son to be a Propitiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I come to the ſecond part of the Application, to wit, to Rules of Duty.</p>
            <p>The firſt whereof will reſpect all in general, to whoſe ears (or eyes) this ſhall come.</p>
            <p>There ſhould be a reſtleſſneſs in Perſons, till there be in 'em an acknowledging, admiring, and improving of the Love of God, particularly of God the Father, and that it was ſo with 'em.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Love of God as brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out in this great inſtance (and ſpeciall Pedge) thereof is to be acknowledged.
<note place="margin">Ingratum ſi dixcris, omnia dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eris.</note> Ingenuous tempers incline Perſons to own ſmall kindneſſes ſhew'd by Men; ſurely then, they cannot think they are of a Gracious temper, who overlook this exceeding
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:154105:19"/>great kindneſs ſhew'd by God. If God had required great things of 'em, they would not have done 'em, who will not do this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This acknowledgment ſhould be</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt (and moſt) inward.
<note place="margin">Chrſtus non patitur by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbolen.</note> The Soul, and all its Powers ſhould be engaged in it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 1.4.</note> The mind ſhould apprehend (and eſteem) it, as that that is undervalued, but cannot be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valued.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Memory ſhould retain lively and powerfull Notions of it, and ſuggeſt 'em to Perſons frequently.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Will ſhould cloſe with and embrace it, in conſenting to Chriſt, and the Propoſals made through <hi>Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. All the Affections ſhould appear vigorouſly in this ſervice.</p>
            <p>So far as Chriſt is preſent, <hi>He</hi> ſhould be delighted in; ſo far as <hi>He</hi> is abſent, <hi>He</hi> ſhould be deſired. Love ſhould in both thoſe ways act towards <hi>Him;</hi> Hope ſhould
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:154105:19"/>expect great things through him; Fear and Hatred ſhould be up, and at work to prevent ſin, as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing and diſhonourable to him, and to his Father that ſent him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This inward acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of DIvine Love is to be Evidenced,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In and by the Lip;
<note place="margin">Outwardly.</note> 
               <hi>Grace</hi> poured into, ſhould be poured out of the lips of Chriſtians. <hi>The Spouſes lips are as a ſcarlet thread, ſmall and ruddy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.3, 11.</note> when ſhe is uttering her Praiſes of the Son who ſhed his Blood, and to the Father that gave him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Yea (and mainly) in and by their Life. Perſons walking ſhould witneſs that they have rightly learned Chriſt:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhould be exalted in their Houſes.</hi> The Fathers Love ſhould reſtrain 'em from ſin, and conſtrain 'em to a courſe of Holy Duties.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In a ſincere and hearty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation to him, and to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:154105:20"/>through him. The whole Soul ſhould cloſe with,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 1.11, 12.</note> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of a whole Saviour. Thoſe excellent ones,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Blake,</hi> Covenant Sealed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> who think that Faith as Juſtifying looks moſt at Chriſt as a Prieſt, and Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinners by his Blood, yet ſay, that the Faith which is Juſtifying hath reſpect alſo to his Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick and Prieſtly Office; and is for being taught and ruled by him. And this leads to the laſt Head, under this firſt Rule of Duty.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The improvement of God the Fathers Love ſhould be ſhewed in a cordial and conſtant Obedience to Chriſt.</hi> Of the Obedience of Faith we read, and without doubt <hi>the Faith will not carry to Heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>James</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>that doth not carry to Obedience. They that honour the Son,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 5.23, 24.</note> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with his Precepts, <hi>honour the Father that ſent him.</hi> To Rule as well as recover Sinners; to ſave them in the way of Sanctifying them.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:154105:20"/>
            <p>The Second Rule of Duty, which doth alſo refer to all that ſhall be Readers (or Hearers) hereof, is,</p>
            <p>Perſons ſhould put this upon a fair Iſſue and Tryal, whether or no they have yet anſwered the Love of God the Father,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5.</note> in lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hold of his Son, the great <hi>Propitiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That I and others, when on this point, may be very ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: Is there not a cauſe?</p>
            <p>I ſhall before I lay down Marks (or Notes) of Tryal, preſent ſome Motives to our Trying our ſelves.</p>
            <p>The firſt Motive is, The Caſe is of great importance; and great matters are not to be ſlightly paſſed over.</p>
            <p>If we have not laid hold on Chriſt,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 5.12.</note> we are in as miſerable a condition as can eaſily be thought of. If we have done it, and have not the knowledge of it, we ſhall be in a want of Comfort.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:154105:21"/>
            <p n="2">2. The thing (if real) is know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and diſcoverable. As there are Exhortations to Self-exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5.</note> as a Duty that lies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in mens reach, ſo ſundry in the uſe of it have been brought to know their ſtate and frame.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Through neglect of Tryal, ſeveral (yea, moſt) Perſons are at a loſs, and know not their own ſelves.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some of the Children of the Bride-Chamber are in Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe the Bridegroom is not with them; not ſo with them, as that they ſhould diſcern him.</p>
            <p>But 2. far more err on the more dangerous hand; they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, and take that for believing, and lay a falſe claim to the Lord Jeſus,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.17.</note> and ſay, <hi>They are rich, when they are miſerably poor.</hi> Many have no more of Chriſt, ſave the Name of Chriſt; others have no more of him but the Notion of him; and a third ſort have no
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:154105:21"/>more of him but the Vizor or appearance of him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Without diligence in this work of Tryal, there is little hope that there ſhould be a true deciſion and determination of the point.</p>
            <p>Where that Faith is that doth apprehend Chriſt, it may be but as a grain of Muſtard-ſeed, very ſmall, and ſo lye leſs open to ſight.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is a feigned and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Faith, that is ſo like the unfeigned and ſincere one, that it muſt be a work of time (and care) and there is need of help from above to diſtinguiſh them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is of great uſe (and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage) to Perſons to know how things ſtand with them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If they find they have not an Intereſt in this <hi>Propitiation,</hi> this may prove a good ſtep to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the attainment of it, by putting on a Mournful Prayer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſeeking after it.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:154105:22"/>
            <p n="2">2. If they find that they are Perſons of ſo good an Intereſt, how may their Hearts leap for joy?
<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 5.12.</note> He that through his Son is rendred <hi>Propitious</hi> and <hi>Gracious</hi> to to them, will at laſt confer Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Bleſſedneſs on them.</p>
            <p>The Marks or Signs which I ſhall lay down for Perſons to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by in their Trying, will be couched under the four follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Queſtions, wherewith I will adventure to poſe every one that takes me for an Adviſer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Haſt thou felt (as well as ſeen) the need thou ſtandeſt in of Chriſts being a <hi>Propitiation,</hi> and thereupon an Advocate for thee?</p>
            <p>Haſt thou ſeen thy ſins as moats in the Sun abounding? Haſt thou felt them as an intolerable bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then on thee? Hath Divine wrath, as due for them, been frightful to thee? Doſt thou own thy beſt done Duties as inſufficient for the appeaſing of Wrath, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:154105:22"/>of Juſtice, how good ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are in their own place? Art thou afraid of ſetting them in Chriſts place? Some things like theſe may be in Hypocrites; and thoſe things may not at ſome times be ſo evident to (and in) true Believers as they deſire: But where is there an Hypocrite that is <hi>poor in Spirit?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.3.</note> Or a true Believer that in his ordinary frame is not?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Doſt thou, when alone (and meditating on the <hi>Rich Grace</hi> of God in Chriſt Jeſus) cry out, <hi>O the depth!</hi> Are thoſe thoughts in thee, that on a Death-bed were uttered by one of the ableſt and choiceſt of young men, <hi>What me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom</hi> 7.24, 25.</note> 
               <hi>Lord! why me?</hi> Shall ſuch a one as I am have the benefit of this <hi>Propitiation?</hi> Would the Father give his Son, or will the Son give himſelf to me? Hypocrites are apt to admire themſelves, and not <hi>Free-Grace;</hi> or <hi>Free-Grace</hi> in order to ſelf-magnifying. Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:154105:23"/>Chriſtians, when they dare not ſay they have embraced Chriſt, are apt to wonder that he is offered them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hath thine Heart known what it is to be ſupported from the conſideration of the <hi>Love of God,</hi> and his exceeding <hi>Rich Grace</hi> in his Son, when it hath been near ſinking upon a ſight and ſenſe of the numerouſneſs and heinouſneſs of ſin, that hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, yea, o'erturn'd thee? Canſt thou <hi>remember the word</hi> (ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Grace) <hi>upon which God hath cauſed thee to hope?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.49.</note> When ſin reviv'd in <hi>Paul</hi>'s ſenſe of it, it was the diſcovery of <hi>abundant Grace</hi> that upheld him.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13, 14, 15.</note> The unſound Profeſſor knows leſs of Heart-failures; and if he have apprehenſions of <hi>Rich Grace,</hi> he is for making it a Cloak for ſin: And the infirm Believer, that is leſs acquainted with Triumphs, is yet through the diſplays of <hi>Rich Grace,</hi> kept from being ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd up of Troubles.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:154105:23"/>
            <p n="4">4. Art thou deſirous to have thine Heart raiſed and enlarged in love to God? Doſt thou rejoyce ſo far as any have reached Glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Love?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> And when thou canſt feel little more than what one ſtyles Lamenting Love, are there ſome ſtirrings of deſiring Love in thee? Art thou ſtudious to pleaſe God? And beſt pleaſed with thine Heart when it is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt to run in the way of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to him? <hi>If thou loveſt God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 4.19.</note> 
               <hi>it is from his loving thee firſt.</hi> If this Fruit grow in (and from) thee, thou art joyn'd to the Root of <hi>Jeſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I have written all I can (yea, when able Writers have done ſo) many will truſt (as they ſpeak) and not try; they'l take it for granted, they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Jeſus Chriſt the Lord, though they have nothing like a Proof of it.</p>
            <p>Be it known, when men dare not bring their Gold to the Teſt,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:154105:24"/>there is great cauſe to fear, it is not pure and right.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 3.20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>Truth in the inward parts doth affect, and not avoid the Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O that they who are willing to try, were Humble, did attend to the Rule of Tryal, the Word of God, and did wait for the Spirit's ſhines on them!</p>
            <p>The Third Rule of Duty hath a particular reference to thoſe that upon Examination do (or may) find that as yet the Love of God the Father, and his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Son, as a <hi>Propitiation,</hi> have not been believingly embrac'd by them.</p>
            <p>They ſhould attend to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices that are moſt proper for them; whereof,</p>
            <p>The firſt is, Be they willing to entertain Convictions, that the Fathers Love, and the Sons Blood, have hitherto been ſlighted by them.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:154105:24"/>
            <p>In order to their Conviction in general, I ſhall offer what follows.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What mean thoſe low thoughts they have of the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goſpel, wherein Chriſt and his Fathers Grace are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed? The Feet of them that bring glad tidings,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14, 15.</note> ſhould be beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful in their Eyes, but their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are not. Light from Heaven ſhould be welcomed on Earth; but (alas) it is not ſo.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How is it, that when the Goſpel finds ſome Entertainment in their Heads, it hath no better room and reception in their Hearts? Their Hearts do not burn within them, when the joyful ſound is in their Ears.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10.</note> The love of that great Truth is not receiv'd together with it; nor indeed are ſuch with whom I am dealing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous it may be ſo.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Are not thoſe of them that have ſome Notions of the worth of Chriſt, far from a due and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:154105:25"/>practical valuation of him?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Will they ſell all, that they may obtain the Pearl of great price? Is not there ſome ſin or other in the Heart,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.45.</note> to which it cleaveth faſt, with which it will not part for Chriſts ſake? Fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing, or Worldlineſs, or Pride bear ſway in them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Are there not ſome pieces of Service which they will not touch with? eſpecially thoſe of a ſecret and inward Nature? Do they aright come to Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28, 29.</note> who reject his Yoke?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Do they when their Duties have been largeſt, and their gifts higheſt, keep up a ſharp Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite to Chriſt and Free-Grace?</p>
            <p>And now I will offer ſome paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages for the Conviction both of the Profane, and of thoſe that are at beſt but <hi>Civilians,</hi> mere <hi>Moraliſts,</hi> or <hi>Formaliſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as to the former ſort,</p>
            <p>With what face (or colour) can they ſay they have received
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:154105:25"/>
               <hi>Jeſus</hi> into their Hearts, and have the Fathers Love ſhed abroad in them, who are overmuch wicked,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.17. <hi>I remember with what ſeriouſneſs a worthy Brother,</hi> Mr. H. Newcome <hi>Preached thereon.</hi>
               </note> as the Preachers Phraſe is.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Wallow in the mire of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, or run into exceſs in Drink, or over reach thoſe they Trade with, or inure their tongues to vain Swearing, Curſing, or Reviling.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Add one of thoſe Enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities to another, having on them ſundry black and broad ſpots at once.</p>
            <p>And 3. Add Rebellion to ſin, hating to be Reformed; riſing up againſt the Reproofs under which they ſhould fall down. Is Chriſt an Head,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12.</note> to which ſuch Corrupt Members are joyned? Is ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs conſiſtent with Graces Teaching? And ſo I fall on poſing thoſe who go no further than the form of Godlineſs.</p>
            <p>Who, 1. In abſtaining from Evil, are onely ſollicitous about abſtaining from more open Evils.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:154105:26"/>The filthineſs that is in the Spirit (to wit,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Contrary to</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1.</note> Pride, Malice, Luke-warmneſs, and Worldlineſs) they indulge.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their abſtinence from evil is ſeparated from diligence in good; they think it enough not to bear bad Fruit, though they be Barren as to what is good; as if not flying out into Rebellion was enough to make a good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. In doing Duties, they are partial, picking and chooſing, and onely taking the cheaper; ſerving the Lord with what coſts them leaſt; not communing with their own Hearts in ſelf-examination, not labouring to work truths up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (and into) their Hearts by Meditation; not keeping up a Watch and Guard over their Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Souls.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They are not for exerciſing their Spirits in the exerciſes they are engag'd in;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>James</hi> 5.17.</note> they are not for Praying earneſtly (or in Prayer)
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:154105:26"/>nor for Praiſing God with their whole Hearts, nor for hearing,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.1.</note> that they may Live.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They when exerciſing ſome of the ſtrength of their Spirits, are not for exerciſing the Graces of Gods Spirit. They cannot call forth Faith, Love, and Zeal, who are void of them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3.</note> They are not for exalting Chriſt above (and in the cloſe of) Duties, nor glorying in him as the Lord their Righteouſneſs, covering their ſins, and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Souls acceptable to God.</p>
            <p>Let theſe know, that as yet the Free grace of God in Chriſt hath not a ſpecial influence on them, nor are they peculiarly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted therein.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Advice is, Be they perſuaded to weigh well that their preſent ſtate is not a ſtate to be reſted in.</p>
            <p>Be it known, that the ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt argues,</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:154105:27"/>
            <p n="1">1. An Underſtanding dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly dark, that hath not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd, 1. The indiſpenſible want of him; that he is more needed than daily Bread.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 4.10</note> God can preſerve mens Bodies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that, but will not ſave their Souls without him. Nor yet, 2. The incomparable worth of him. Did Men kow the gift of God, and how this Sun out-ſhines all leſſer Stars, ſo that they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appear at and on his appearance; they could not but fall in Love with him, and follow hard after him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is alſo an Argument of an Heart deſperately hard, hardened through divers Luſts; particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Pride. The Heart thinks too highly of it ſelf to go unto Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3, 4. <hi>John</hi> 1.11</note> to be its Righteouſneſs, and too meanly of his Service, to ſubmit to him as its Ruler.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Senſuality. It prefers fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Puddles before the River of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:154105:27"/>God; and had rather have its Reſidence in Styes, than in his pure preſence.</p>
            <p>And it is a great Truth (but no great Wonder) that this ſin doth immediately ſhut Perſons out of Heaven, and under Wrath; what Remedy is there for thoſe with whom the great Goſpel-remedy is at an undervalue? Will not all the Curſes of the Law (and with them an <hi>Anathema,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22.</note> 
               <hi>Maranatha</hi>) fall on ſuch as <hi>Love not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> nor have recourſe to him, and to his Fathers Love, in him, that they may do ſo? Whither will they Appeal, that are caſt at the Mercy-ſeat?</p>
            <p>I will next apply my ſelf to the notoriouſly Vicious; and oh that God would ſay to them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah</hi> 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>Get ye from theſe Tents; Haſte out of this Sodom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Know they, their Crimes are exceedingly aggravated from the tenders of the great <hi>Propitiation</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:154105:28"/>out of the Fathers Rich Grace made to 'em.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Are they not againſt clear Light? In this Glaſs may be ſeen, 1. How deep the ſtain and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of ſin is, which onely his Blood, who is God, can fetch out, ſo that it ſhall not be ſeen with an avenging Eye. 2. How greatly the Nature (as well as the Will) of God is againſt ſin; yea, how all his Attributes op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſin?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32.</note> 
               <hi>He ſpared not his own Son, but gave him up to a Curſed Death, when he undertook to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for it.</hi> 3. How willing (as well as able) both the Father and the Son are to receive Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents into favour. Doth not Chriſt's death ſet out this to the Life, and with their Love is that of the Spirit preſented in the Goſpel? witneſs the moving La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations over ſinners,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2, 3. <hi>John</hi> 5.40.</note> the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Exhortations on 'em, and winning Invitations to 'em: And ſo,</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:154105:28"/>
            <p n="2">2. Are not their ill courſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt dear Love, yea, againſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the higheſt Love, as to the ſpring Evidences and Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of it? Do they not ſtrike at the Heart of every Perſon in the Godhead?</p>
            <p>And will not theſe blows re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound and fall on their Heads that give 'em?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21.</note> Will not this be the Condemnation of thouſands? they (with the reſiſtance of Light and Love) expected that God ſhould ſave 'em in their ſins, who would have have ſav'd 'em from 'em.</p>
            <p>The Application is now to fall on thoſe that reſt on this ſide Chriſt the true Reſt, though in thoſe cleaner ways to Hell (as ſome ſpeak) Civility and Formality. This is not their Reſt, nor ſhould be made ſo one hour. Till ſuch Perſons have Union to and Communion with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and his Father,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12.</note> They are in the World with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God in the World: They
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:154105:29"/>have a better Air than Heathens, but have not better Hearts, at leaſt not a better inward ſtate than they. They have more Light, but not more Spiritual ſight: They have more Church-Priviledges, but no more ſaving Grace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their Services, how ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſoever and taking with Men, are unacceptable to God, if we ſpeak of full and abſolute (and not of comparative) acceptance; their Fruit is not to Perfection,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5.</note> and will not be to Salvation, not growing on or from the Tree of Life.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They have no Title to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 3. <hi>laſt.</hi>
               </note> but are Children and Heirs of Wrath. Their Righteouſneſs doth not exceed (probably it doth not equallize) the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. <hi>laſt.</hi>
               </note> It is Chriſt alone that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers from the Wrath to come, and he onely delivers thoſe that are in him.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:154105:29"/>
            <p>The laſt advice as to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate is, cry they, pray they, get they all their Friends to cry (and pray) for a change of their ſtate and frame, that they may on good grounds ſay, that Jeſus Chriſt is a <hi>Propitiation</hi> for their ſins, and that the Father that ſent him to be ſo, hath ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted him as ſuch. O that the Lord, who imploys one ſo weak as I am, would Honour me in making me an Inſtrument of their Converſion!</p>
            <p n="1">1. Study they (to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) that they do as really need an Intereſt in this Bleſſed <hi>Propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation,</hi> as any in the World can do.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Have they not many great ſins to be removed off from their Souls, and out of God's ſight? Did they not fall as far (and foully) as any in <hi>Adam?</hi> Did they not derive, as guilty Perſons,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. &amp; 7.24.</note> ſo filthy Natures from him? Is there not in every one of 'em a Root of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:154105:30"/>bitterneſs? Hath not this Root been fruitful in the unfruitful works of Darkneſs? If all their ſins (particularly thoſe of Omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) were ſet in order before 'em: If onely thoſe that have been more directly againſt the Love of the Father and the Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, were preſented to 'em, would they not be as a vaſt and terrible Army? And if the heightning Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of 'em were ſhewed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with 'em, would they not render 'em ſtill more frightful?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Be they fully perſuaded, that no Righteouſneſs which they can call their own, will avail or ſignifie any thing, as to the ato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of God, and rendring him Propitious and Gracious to 'em. The Bed is too ſhort, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtretch themſelves thereon: The Covering is too narrow, they cannot wrap themſelves therein. The injur'd Juſtice of God being infinite,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 7.20.</note> cannot be righted by
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:154105:30"/>any finite payments made to it: <hi>Thouſands of Rams,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah</hi> 6.5, 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>and ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Rivers of Oyl, are inſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Make they a juſt Account, that to their Salvation a renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Natures is needful: As they are indebted, ſo they are diſeaſed; as they need Pardons, ſo they need Cares; if God ſave 'em, he'l heal 'em.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Doubt they not of the All-ſufficiency of Chriſt's <hi>Propitiation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 6.37 &amp; 7.37.</note> or of the freeneſs of his Father to make over to 'em the benefit thereof, upon their coming in, and yielding themſelves to him. Aſſuredly, if they can once get a ſight of the face of Jeſus Chriſt,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6.</note> they may with comfort behold the Glory of God in it. All the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Attributes will appear then amiable, all the ways of God will be rendred eaſie, and all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences of God will become pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable; even chaſtiſing ones or Rods will have Honey on the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:154105:31"/>end of 'em, which they ſhall taſte.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That they may be brought nigh to the Father and the Son, and ſhare in their Loves, wait they in the uſe of a plain clear practical Miniſtry, that the Holy Spirit may deſcend on 'em, and they may experience the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and powerfulneſs of his drawings. God not ſeldom ſpeaks to mens Hearts by his Miniſters as his Mouth; and Oh that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons longed to find the Holy Spirit!</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.17.</note> A revealing Spirit, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 'em the King in his excellent enamouring Beauty.</p>
            <p n="2">2. An inclining Spirit, bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their wills,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.3.</note> and bringing 'em over to embrace him whom they apprehend.</p>
            <p n="3">3. An enabling Spirit, empow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring 'em to come to him that is able to ſave 'em to the uttermoſt, from ſins reigning Power here, as well as from its ruining power
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:154105:31"/>hereafter. O for a Spirit of Faith! Is it not much more precious than Gold or Pearls? Though it do not at all make the <hi>Propitiation</hi> for our ſins, it makes it ours.</p>
            <p>Leſt all I have ſaid be as if it was unſaid to thoſe who moſt need it,</p>
            <p>I ſhall (before I come to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect my Speech to the Regenerate) ſet before the Unregenerate, and ſuch as continue to ſlight the Rich Grace of God in Chriſt, ſome moving Motives.</p>
            <p>One is, Death is on its way towards 'em, and every ſtep they take they are a ſtep nearer to it: Their Glaſs is continually run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and how few Sands remain in it, it is not for them to know. What if it ſhould lay hold on them before they have laid hold on this <hi>Propitiation?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 18.14</note> Would it not be as it hath been accounted of terrible things the moſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible?</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:154105:32"/>
            <p>For, 2. if they come not to Chriſt, he will in Judgment come againſt them; and as he is the ſweeteſt Friend, ſo he is the ſoreſt Foe.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. <hi>laſt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The wrath of the Lamb</hi> is to Grandees that are to fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it full of Terror. They that will not have him as their Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, cannot flye from him as their Judge. And to their ſhame and ſorrow it will appear.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This Judge is All-knowing: No ſin hath been committed ſo ſecretly, as to ſcape his Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance. He will bring to light the moſt hidden works of Darkneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He is alſo moſt Juſt, and cannot be Bribed; nor will any make offers of that ſort to him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He is Powerful, and they that fall into his Revenging hands can make no eſcape out of 'em:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 33.13, 14.</note> His diſpleaſure which cannot well be endured, cannot at all be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Will not the Torments which they ſhall be adjudged to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:154105:32"/>have ſundry of the ſharpeſt ſtings in 'em?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Will they not have the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culative knowledge of the great Love which God made offers of, that ſo their ſin may appear ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſinful,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 3.19.</note> and their Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings moſt righteous? Knowledge ſhall be increaſed, that Sorrow may be ſo: Even where there is utter darkneſs, there will be light that is terrifying. The thoughts of Mercy that were moſt ſweet in Life, will be more bitter than many Deaths, becauſe it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Will they not have a ſin to anſwer (and ſuffer) for, which is not chargeable on Devils, who never had Chriſt (and Grace in him) held forth to 'em?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3.</note> The Blood of Chriſt muſt needs lye heavy on thoſe on whom the guilt of it lyes, becauſe the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of it was made light of.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Yet the day of Grace laſteth, and the Door of Hope continues
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:154105:33"/>open.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.7.</note> 
               <hi>If the wicked forſake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts, and turn to the Lord, making the Son of God his Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, he ſhall in no wiſe be caſt out.</hi> There is in Chriſt vertue to take away ſins againſt Chriſt; and the Fathers Bowels will yearn over a Penitent that hath been a Prodigal.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 15.20.</note> The Lord turn ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that they may be turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed!</p>
            <p>The Fourth Rule of Duty hath a particular eye upon thoſe that are Intereſted in the Son of God as a <hi>Propitiation,</hi> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Love of his Father.</p>
            <p>They ſhould be found attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to (and in) the Services that are proper to (and for) 'em.</p>
            <p>The firſt Service is, Muſing on (and weighing) the exceeding great Love of God the Father, as manifeſted in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Beſides, what they have read under this weak hand concerning it, they are (here) to read
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:154105:33"/>thereof, as it is conſidered
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>This way the Text leads; ſo doth Rom.</hi> 5.7, 8.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively.</p>
            <p n="1">1. With the Love of Men to Men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. With the Love of Men to God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. With other expreſſions of the Love of God to Men.</p>
            <p>Hereby it will be evident, that this Love is a Noneſuch.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What is the Love of Men to Men? Even of thoſe whoſe Love is ſtrongeſt, in compariſon of this Love?</p>
            <p>Doth it not far ſurpaſs the love of the moſt loving Friends? Though Hiſtories relate won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous things concerning ſome that ſtood in that relation; and the Scriptures ſpeak of
<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.1. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.26.</note> the near bond (and tye) which Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip knit between <hi>Jonathan</hi> and <hi>David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, 1. Though in Friendſhip there is an uniting of Hearts, yet the Love we are conſidering cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed an Union of Natures, of an
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:154105:34"/>infinite and finite one,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>laſt.</hi>
               </note> of God and Man, in one Perſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Friends may, and many times do ſee an amiableneſs (and ſo ground for Love) in another; but God ſaw no ſuch thing in fallen Man:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. <hi>in initio.</hi>
               </note> He ſaw what might cauſe loathing, but could not ſee any Lovelineſs in him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Doth not this Love (far and far) paſs the Love of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents? Though we uſually ſay, This Love deſcends,
<note place="margin">Amor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendit.</note> and its mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being downwards, is ſwifter and ſtronger.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam</hi> 1.26.</note> The Love of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (of Mothers that are Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) hath a peculiar accent on it.</p>
            <p>But, 1. When Parents Love their Children,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Suum cui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> proprium. Coloſ.</hi> 1.21.</note> they love their own, and ſuch in whom they ſee their Image; whereas God loved ſinners, when a lienated from him, and bearing a contrary Image to him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nature leads Parents to love their Children; but Gods
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:154105:34"/>Love to ſinners is of pure Grace.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Love of Parents, even of Nurſing-Mothers, may decline; <hi>A Mother may forget a ſucking Child:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.14, 15.</note> But the Love of God knows no ſuch declinings.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Doth not his Love exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly exceed the Love of Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.24.</note> who yet are nearer to their Wives than Parents are to their Children: Children are part of Parents; but a mans Wife is as himſelf.</p>
            <p>Yea, 1. Whereas there is a ſpecial relation which is the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Husbands Love to his Wife: God loved
<note n="*" place="margin">Amor benevolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae.</note> ſinners, when they ſtood in no ſpecial Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to him, but were his utter Enemies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Many Wives are very love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but no ſinners (as ſuch) are ſo.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25.</note> Husbands are bound to Love their Wives; Gods Love of well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſhing to ſinners is a moſt free Act.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:154105:35"/>
            <p>I may add, What is our Love to our ſelves unto the Love of God, the love of his good-will to ſinners?</p>
            <p>Our Love is founded in Nature, and is withall ſubject to inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy: Gods Love is moſt Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and beſt ordered in all things.</p>
            <p>I now come to ask,</p>
            <p>What is the love of Men (of the beſt Men) to God, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively to Gods Love to Men?</p>
            <p>I the rather inſiſt on this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe my Text doth ſo; which ſaith, <hi>Herein is love, not that we loved God, but that he loved us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, 1. God's Love to us is a leading Love:
<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 4.19.</note> At beſt, our Love to him is but an after-love. He drinks the firſt Draught,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 15.16.</note> we do but pledge him; He beſtows Love, we do but
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Amorem reſpondere.</hi> This way went Mr. <hi>S. E.</hi> at <hi>Mottram.</hi>
               </note> repay it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God's Love to us is a cauſing Love; ours is but a cauſed one. Ours is the Fruit, his is the Root. His more Glorious than the Sun,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:154105:35"/>ours no more than a Ray.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.20, 21.</note> Our firſt diſpoſition was not to love God, but to hate him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though the expreſſions of God's Love to us be of Grace, yet Love is his very Nature; it is Eſſential to him. He is Love,
<note place="margin">
                  <p>1 <hi>John</hi> 4.8, 16. <hi>Eſſentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Biſhop</hi> Davenant <hi>on Colof. p.</hi> 27.</p>
               </note> but in us love to him is but an accident and quality; we may have Love, but cannot ſay, we are Love.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He is altogether lovely: All Beauties and Excellencies which ſhould attract and draw out love, are found in him; He is worthy to be loved: He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves far better love than we have for him; but, in our ſelves conſidered, we are and have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is Love-worthy.</p>
            <p n="5">5. His Love (as hath been over and over hinted) is wholly free.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14.</note> Our love is in a ſort (by and from the conſideration of his) conſtrained.</p>
            <p n="6">6. His Love is as a flame full of ſtrength; whereas our Love
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:154105:36"/>labours under meanneſs, frailneſs, and feebleneſs, &amp; is a ſpark amidſt aſhes.</p>
            <p n="7">7. His Love was from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.3.</note> ours is but a Birth of time.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6.</note> His Love is unchangable; ours is too ſubject to changes.</p>
            <p>The laſt compariſon I would have my Readers to make, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween other manifeſtations of the love of God the Father, and this of his ſending his Son to be a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gods goodneſs invited him to make Man,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.19.</note> and is ſeen in the work of Providence, as well as that of Creation; and in many Providential Diſpenſations it is very conſpicuous and illuſtrious; but the brighteſt Beams break out in Redemption.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Other works were from the Word of God;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28.</note> this was through his Blood that is God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In other works men were not
<note n="*" place="margin">Haud aſſiſtentes.</note> aſſiſting, but this found 'em
<note n="*" place="margin">Reſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> reſiſting.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:154105:36"/>
            <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See at large Dr.</hi> Bates <hi>his Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</hi>
               </note> In other works there was a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play of ſome of Gods Attributes; in this they are all diſplay'd in their Glory. O that good mens thoughts ſtaid on this noble ſubject, till the fire kindled, and their Hearts burn'd within 'em with Love to the whole Trinity! and in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, to the Father and the Son, who are in the Text (and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine) more particularly treated of: And ſo I am led to touch on</p>
            <p>The Second Service, which the Regenerate, who are Intereſted in the great <hi>Propitiation,</hi> and the love of God that ſet him (and it) forth, ſhould be diligent in.</p>
            <p>Their love both to the Father and the Son ſhould be on the growing hand, and be in exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.</p>
            <p>Their love to the Father ſhould ſhew it ſelf in the next nam'd Inſtances.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In an humble and heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breaking Confeſſion of their ſins againſt him. As a Flint may be
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:154105:37"/>broken on a ſoft Cuſhion,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 15.18, 19, 21.</note> ſo may an hard Heart upon the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Divine Love, and that return of Love which it cauſeth. Tears are moſt of all Holy Water, when they flow from an Eye of Faith exerciſed on God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Mercy,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4.</note> and the Sons Merit. God's goodneſs leads to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance thoſe that have too much abuſed it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In a patient and hearty ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Sufferings (and Correction) which this beſt of Fathers inflicteth. His Rods (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the hand of Love) are to be kiſſed;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.41.</note> and the Puniſhment of his Childrens Iniquity is to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. They ſhould learn of their elder Brother, readily to drink of the Cup which he puts into their Hand,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 18.11.</note> though it be a bitter one.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In a chearful active for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs in doing the work which this Father cuts out for 'em, proving themſelves Obedient
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:154105:37"/>Children.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13, 14. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14, 15.</note> This great Stream and Torrent of Love ſhould carry to an abounding in Obedience. What ſhould they think too dear for him, who thought not his Son too dear to give to 'em?</p>
            <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13.</note> In an ultimate reſolving of their Thankfulneſs to this Father, the Father of Mercies, from whom (if we regard the Order in the Trinity) they firſt ariſe; to whom (according to Scripture Order) thanks are firſt (and laſt) to be returned.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In a prizing other favours from this higheſt Father, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to (and on account of) this prime favour, the ſending and Sacrificing his Son.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32.</note> Other things are choicer Gifts, becauſe related to (and given with) this Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. From this Sun other Stars derive their Light; Chriſt is the Figure before the numbers of other Gifts that puts the great value on 'em.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:154105:38"/>
            <p>And ſo I come to ſhew,</p>
            <p>That the Regenerate ſhould in an eminent manner ſhew their love to Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His Perſon ſhould be as the Object (ſo in a ſort the Center) of their Affections.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.16</note> 
               <hi>He is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lovely;</hi> and to be loved ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They ſhould move towards him by degrees,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.2.</note> ſo far as the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of him is yet wanted. The Husbands abſence goes to the good Wives heart.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 2. <hi>laſt.</hi>
               </note> The Spouſe deſires Chriſt would be as a Roe for his ſwiftneſs in coming to her. Have not ſome, becauſe they could not be ſo near as they deſired to Chriſt and live, been willing to dye, that they might be nearer him? Are not Duties (is not Heaven) moſt to be prized on account of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23.</note> enjoying Chriſt?</p>
            <p n="2">2. They ſhould reſt in him by delight, ſo far as he is pleaſed to communicate himſelf to 'em. The riſing of the Sun of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:154105:38"/>on (and in) their Souls ſhould make a day there.</p>
            <p>Doth not the Spouſe ſpeak in a triumphing way, when ſhe ſaith, <hi>I am my Beloved's,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.16.2.4.</note> 
               <hi>and my Beloved is mine?</hi> Doth ſhe not ſit under his ſhadow with great Solace, and find his Fruit ſweet to her taſte? Is not his love to her better than Wine? And doth not his Sin-ſlaying and Soul-quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Preſence tend to ſatisfie her Soul as with marrow and fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</p>
            <p>Again, Chriſt's Practice ſhould be the Copy of their Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 2.6.</note> He that was a <hi>Propitiation</hi> for, is to be a Patern to 'em.</p>
            <p>Particularly, 1. In his exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Compaſſion to ſelf-oppoſing ſinners. His Eye affected his Heart,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 6.34.</note> when he ſaw the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude that wanted Spiritual Food, and Hearts to deſire it. His Heart ſet his Eye on weeping over <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 19.41.</note> when he ſaw what her ſinful Inhabitants would
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:154105:39"/>reduce her and themſelves to.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In his reſiſting the Tempter and his Temptations with the Sword of the Spirit, the Word of God:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.</note> When the Prince of this World came, he could not overcome, nor ſtand before theſe Weapons, which were not Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, but mighty through God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In laying <hi>Zion</hi>'s ſorrows near his Heart.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.8. <hi>Acts</hi> 9.4. &amp; 10.38.</note> In all his Churches Afflictions he was Afflicted; was not the Head moſt ſenſible of Wounds to him?</p>
            <p n="4">4. In conforming his will to that of his Father.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.5.</note> In going about doing good. O that the ſame mind that was in his were in our hearts!</p>
            <p>The laſt Rule of Duty is for thoſe that have the Grace to take and follow the good Advices that have been given.</p>
            <p>They may take my Doctrine as a Cordial: May they may find its chearing Vertue!</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:154105:39"/>
            <p n="1">1. Under all kinds of Diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement and Diſtreſs. Whether, 1. They be from what they find without 'em. Do they meet with many, and thoſe heavy Croſſes? Yet the Curſe ſhall not come to 'em.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.12, 13.</note> He that was a <hi>Propitiation</hi> was alſo made a Curſe for 'em, that they might be freed from the Curſe due to 'em. The Love of God the Father ſhall not be leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſened (or leſs manifeſted) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are in Suffering: Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents Hearts uſe to be moſt open to their ſick Children.</p>
            <p>Or, 2. If they have inward ſorrows, and be acquainted with thoſe troubles that follow the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of God's face,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30 6, 7.</note> they may write on it, They have not loſt their Fathers Affection, though they miſs ſome deſirable expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of it. Shall not the Sun break through preſent Clouds? Will not the Son on account of his being a <hi>Propitiation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 2.1, 2.</note> be an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate for 'em, that they may at
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:154105:40"/>laſt be comforted, and in the mean time ſupported?</p>
            <p>Again, From this Doctrine an Uſe of Conſolation is rightly drawn as to thoſe I am treating with.</p>
            <p>In all Duties, whether ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary or extraordinary; whether Prayer, wherein they ſpeak to God; or Self-examination, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they ſpeak with themſelves; or Hearing, wherein God ſpeaks to them.</p>
            <p>Though none of theſe Duties have Perfection,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2.10.</note> the <hi>Propitiation</hi> which God the Father hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the Son hath. So.</p>
            <p>I will give a further touch on one Ordinance, wherein the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of this Doctrine (to prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Receivers) uſeth to flow freely, and that is the Holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lord, which is not to be perverted (as by the Papiſts it is) into a <hi>Propitiatory Sacrifice;</hi> but it is a Commemoration, yea, and withall a Communication of ſuch a Sacrifice.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:154105:40"/>
            <p>Yea,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Doctor</hi> Cudworth</note> and is well called a Feaſt upon him that was Offered as a <hi>Propitiation;</hi> and ſo is to be Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated with joy and thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which the word <hi>Euchariſt</hi> (which hath long been one of its names) implyeth.</p>
            <p>Both the Elements, and all the actions about 'em, tend to fill their Hearts with gladneſs who uſe that Communion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Penitentially;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10.</note> looking with pierced Souls on their pierced Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Applicatorily; putting the finger of Faith into his Wounds.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Charitably; pitying their Enemies, as he pityed them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Longingly;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.10.</note> that the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Ordinance may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company it. Is not Chriſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in given to 'em, who was given for 'em? Doth not God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhew that he is ſatisfied? And ſhall not this ſatisfie and ſolace 'em? And as in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration they may ſee the Heart
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:154105:41"/>of God the Father,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Baxter <hi>in ſeveral pieces.</hi>
               </note> and in the Commemoration the fulneſs of the Son: So in the Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it is made out, that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the Comforter is free to come from both with Comfort to 'em.</p>
            <p>O that mine own Heart had been more inflamed with God the Fathers Love, and my Faith more exerciſed on his Son as Sacrificed, when I was writing thereof! O that my Readers Hearts may feel that force in theſe things which mine hath not!</p>
            <p>May the Lord, in whoſe hand all Hearts are, awaken thoſe that have ſlighted <hi>Rich Grace!</hi> May Honeſt Hearts find that Grace as ſufficient for, ſo effectual in 'em. <hi>Amen</hi> and <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:154105:41"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Third Inſtance</hi> OF THE RICHES OF GRACE: TO WIT, <hi>God the Father pouring out his SPIRIT.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Zech. 12.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And I will pour upon the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> and the Inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> of the Spirit of Grace <hi>—</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AS there are outbreakings of Light before the appearance of the body of the Sun;
<note place="margin">Ortus Solit luminis.</note> ſo there
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:154105:42"/>were outbreakings of the Goſpel, long before the Sun of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs his appearing in the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature.</p>
            <p>Though my Text was delivered in the time of the Law, the Truth delivered in it had a ſpecial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Goſpel-times; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, I find that day found mentioned in the Verſe before it Interpreted.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Synopſ. Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic. from</hi> Druſius.</note> To ſtrike all through as to that point, we read under the hand of the Evangeliſt S. <hi>John,</hi> that the latter part of the Verſe before us was fulfilled,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 17.37.</note> when our dear Lords ſides were pierced.</p>
            <p>One,
<note place="margin">Junius.</note> whoſe Praiſe is in the Church, is for obſerving the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallels (and Agreements) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween places in the Old and New Teſtament, hath told us, that the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves have not dared to deny that this Text hath its Eye on the Kingdom of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I deny not that the words have firſt their face on the <hi>Jews;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Dioda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti,</hi> &amp;c.</note> and ſome Divines conceive, they look
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:154105:42"/>as far as to that National Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of 'em, which not a few look for. Yet I affirm, that as the believing <hi>Gentiles</hi> are grafted into the ſame Olive the <hi>Jews</hi> were once in,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17.</note> ſo the Fruit of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe may be expected, and ſhall be reaped by 'em.</p>
            <p>One that excelled, hath ſaid,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> J.C.</note> that by the Houſe of <hi>David</hi> we are to underſtand the Church of Chriſt:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2.1, 2, 3.</note> And was not this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe (as well as that in <hi>Joel</hi>) in part fulfilled, when there was a plentiful effuſion of the Spirit?</p>
            <p>If the ſhower fall on the Jews, ſprinklings may be on other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. On this Promiſe I have all reaſon to write <hi>Precious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which we have,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Donor or Giver, God the Father; not excluding the Son. He is the firſt Perſon in the Godhead;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 1.4.</note> and the Promiſe of the Spirit is called the Promiſe of (or by) the Father.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:154105:43"/>
            <p n="2">2. The gift (as is hinted) is the Holy Spirit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The manner of the Fathers communicating the Spirit, which is expreſſed by pouring out, and denoteth freeneſs and fulneſs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Adjunct (or Epithet) of this Spirit: He is ſtyled, <hi>The Spirit of Grace;</hi> not onely as work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grace, but as given out of pure Grace.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Subjects recipient of the Spirit, <hi>the Houſe of David,</hi> &amp;c. Even ſuch as had their Hands in the Blood of Chriſt. And now we have fair way and room for</p>
            <p>This Doctrine. <hi>The pouring out of the Holy Spirit is an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Evidence of the Grace of God the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the Son, ſo the Spirit is his Gift.</p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>Quaere</hi> to be reſolved is, What is here meant by the Spirit?</p>
            <p>And the firſt Anſwer is, I am not (nor are my betters) ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:154105:43"/>to go in their narrow Path that ſome take, who allow the Lord to make no further Promiſe of the Spirit, ſave of that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Grace and Aid of his, which leaves the refuſers thereof with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuſe;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Trueman, <hi>in all his Pieces.</hi>
               </note> as if none could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſuch ſpecial efficacious over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powering Influences as do infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly bring over Perſons to God.</p>
            <p>Is not this to make the effuſion of the Spirit rather an effect of Juſtice, than an iſſue of purely Free Mercy?</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rond Biſhop</hi> Reynolds.</note> Is it not well accounted hard in thoſe that diſpute for their own Liberty as to receiving Grace, to deny the Lord his liberty as to giving it? Shall we ſay (or think) that he onely gives
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Poſſe, velle, non velle. See Phil.</hi> 2.12, 13. <hi>and Doctor</hi> Ward <hi>on it.</hi>
               </note> the power to will, but the act of willing what is ſpiritually good is without any peculiar cauſing of his? Doth not my Text clear this, that when God pours out his Spirit, he will attain an end and effect of the beſt kind? Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:154105:44"/>ſhall look on Chriſt Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, and Repentingly mourn for him.</p>
            <p>The Second Anſwer is, I no way doubt, we are here by the Spirit to underſtand the Graces and Sanctifying Operations of the Spirit. Do not theſe moſt pure and bleſſed Streams partake of the Nature (and ſo of the Name) of the Fountain? The Child is called after the Father, and ſo is the effect after the cauſe, by a Figure much uſed in Holy Writ.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Mr.</hi> Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton. <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. Evan.</hi>
               </note> One who was Famous in both <hi>Englands,</hi> by the Spirit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands the univerſal Created frame of inherent ſaving Grace. Of receiving this Spirit we are moſt capable, as it is alſo of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering and increaſing in us.</p>
            <p>The Third Anſwer, I ſee no cauſe to decline the Company of thoſe great men, who hold, that where the Grace of the Spirit is given (and received) there is a peculiar preſence of the Spirit of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:154105:44"/>Grace, the Rivulets are not cut off from the River; and I find excellent ones willing to Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret my Text of the Spirit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as joyn'd with the Graces given by him.</p>
            <p>To prevent miſtakes and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtandings,</p>
            <p>I add, 1. I am far from going ſo far as ſome have done, who have aſſerted not onely a preſence of the Spirit, but ſuch a Perſonal Preſence of the Spirit with the Sanctified, as that they become one Perſonally with him.</p>
            <p>Is not this Tenent rightly charged,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>By Mr.</hi> Barret.</note> as affirming an Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Third as well as the Second Perſon in the Trinity, and the dwelling of the fulneſs of the Godhead in the Members as well as the Head of the Church? Can this be freed from the charge
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>By Mr.</hi> Hollingſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth.</note> of dividing the Spirit, and limiting him, or ſeeming ſo to do, whilſt it affirms, that he is Perſonally here or there, in this and the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:154105:45"/>other Saint, and is not in other places and perſons.</p>
            <p>All care is to be had leſt we debaſe the Spirit, or Deifie the Spiritual.</p>
            <p>It is not to be thought, that the Spirit is ſo in any Perſons,
<note place="margin">Trough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton <hi>on Pſal.</hi> 45.</note> as that he ſhould be the immediate and formal exerter of their Acts. It is not he, but they, that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and Believe, though he worketh theſe works in and for 'em.
<note place="margin">Agens li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berrimum.</note> Nor doth he work in any as a neceſſary and natural Agent, but in all he doth is a Voluntier and moſt free Agent.</p>
            <p>Yet,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. <hi>laſt.</hi>
               </note> I have long been ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, that the Communion (or Communication) of the Holy Ghoſt himſelf, as well as the Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and Love of God the Father, is with Gracious Perſons.</p>
            <p>He himſelf is the Author, Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, and Perfecter of Grace. By him perſons are quickned, ſtrengthned, ſealed, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:154105:45"/>They who had no touch of <hi>Enthuſiaſm</hi> (or <hi>Phanaticiſm</hi>) have made this Obſervation, that the Spirits inhabitation is ſpoken of as joyned to the love of God, as ſhed abroad in the Heart, as diſtinguiſhed from the New Man,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5, 8, 9. <hi>See</hi> Pool <hi>againſt</hi> Biddle.</note> from being in the Spirit. A late Famous
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Tuckney.</note> Profeſſor profeſſeth his full belief, that the Holy Ghoſt himſelf is given to and dwelleth in Believers; and from their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtyled <hi>the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> it is genuinely inferred,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri <hi>metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, part</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 216. <hi>ut foedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</hi>
               </note> that they ſtand nearly related to his Perſon; as on other accounts it is concluded, that he is nearer than we can think to his own Grace, and works in a Covenant-way on and in the Gracious.</p>
            <p>Some Proofs that the pouring out of the Spirit argues the Free Rich Grace of the Father, are now next us.</p>
            <p>The Firſt whereof is drawn from the conſideration of the Dignity and Office of the Spirit.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:154105:46"/>As it is ſaid of the Son,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>that he thought it no Robbery to be equal with God</hi> (that is, the Father) the ſame is applicable to the Spirit. And as he is a Perſon in the Godhead, he is that Perſon that applyes the love of both the other Perſons to us.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Sibbs, <hi>Conc. ad lerum.</hi>
               </note> From the ſweet dropper ſee words that bear this ſenſe. All things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the Divine Eſſence, by the Mediation of the Perſons therein, and amongſt the Perſons in the following Order; from the Father, through the Son, by the Spirit. Is he not the Spirit of Grace?</p>
            <p>The Second Proof is fetch'd from our conſidering the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (yea, vileneſs) of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons on whom the Spirit is poured before he is ſo. Are they not ſuch on whom the Father might juſtly pour out his wrath? Are they not (Naturally) in their Blood? under guilt and filth? Was it not thus with thoſe Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:154105:46"/>of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10.</note> who were Crucifiers of Chriſt? The Spirit finds though he leaves not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in a woful (yea, wilful) ſtate at frame.</p>
            <p>The Third Proof is founded on a due viewing and weighing in what manner (and meaſure) the Spirit is communicated: Is he not poured out moſt largely and plenteouſly? Is not he in thoſe that are ſpiritual as a Well and Spring of Living Water? Is there not reſpect had to him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 4.14. &amp; 7.38, 39</note> when it is ſaid, <hi>Out of their Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies flow Rivers of living water?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is not every drop from the Spirit moſt ſweet and gracious? What Grace is there then in Floods from him?</p>
            <p>The Fourth Proof ariſeth from the Bleſſed Conſequents and Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects that follow the pouring out of the Spirit: ſome of which are pointed at in the Context.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Is he not in thoſe that are his a ſpirit of Prayer? And are
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:154105:47"/>not Grace and Supplication joyn'd together?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10.</note> I know the Spirit of Prayer is far, and far before the gift of Prayer; but what gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Chriſtian ſhould not value both? Hath not he hath hath the Spirit of Prayer a Key to Heaven, and its Treaſure?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Dod.</note> Was ever Man quite undone, that was in a Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing frame?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is he not alſo the Spirit of Faith? Doth he not open the Souls Eye, as well as unbare that Object its Saviour? Is he not the Spirit of Revelation?
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13.</note> Doth he not help ſuch as are ſtung with (and for) ſin, to look on Chriſt, as ſatisfying Divine Juſtice,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.17.</note> that he may ſatisfie Humane deſire? And is not the look Healing?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Is he not withall a Spirit of Repentance? Cauſing that mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ſin that is of a Godly ſort (or according to God) and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring ſweetly of his Grace; being Spiritual,</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:154105:47"/>
            <p n="1">1. As to the riſe of it; being from him as working Conviction, which implyes a clear abiding ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicatory diſcovery of ſin; and compunction, which carries in it griefs and fears.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to the grounds of it; being, 1. For ſin, as croſſing the Divine Law, and not onely as procuring Divine wrath, and ſo is for the evil of ſin, and for all ſorts of ſins. 2. For ſin, as piercing Chriſt; and ſo hath love to him at the bottom of it, and will be as a Spring ſtill flowing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the Fruits of it; which are ſuch as theſe: 1. Weaning the Heart in ſome good meaſure from the World, and moderating, 1. Its Joy in the enjoyment of it. 2. Its ſorrow for loſſes in it. 3. Tending to break the Heart from ſin. And 3. Rendring it more ſoft and flexible to God and Goodneſs.</p>
            <p>Now, who that gives what I have written the weight that
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:154105:48"/>belongs to it, that takes a true meaſure: Who the Holy Spirit is, and how, and on whom he is poured, being as Floods on dry and bad ground, and producing ſuch an alteration thereof, and Fruits therein, can refrain from ſaying, Here's Grace to a Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der?</p>
            <p>May this Holy Spirit, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whom I am writing, and others are to read, teach us to make a right</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Application;</hi> which ſhall be firſt by way of</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Information.</hi> Sincere Chriſtians are under the greateſt Bonds (and Obligations) poſſible to God, particularly to God the Father. Who can by ſearching find out how vaſtly they are indebted to his Grace? Have they not all of 'em received a meaſure of the ſame Spirit,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12.</note> though all of 'em have not received the ſame mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Spirit? Of his great Love in giving his Son, we have
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:154105:48"/>touched, In that he who gave his Son to obtain, ſhould alſo give his Spirit to apply Salvation to 'em. They whom this Spirit animateth and acteth, are the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and ſhould be the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets of exceeding Rich Grace.</p>
            <p>Leſt ſome that I have in mine Eye (and on mine Heart) ſhould to (and in) their own wrong, put away this word and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of it from 'em, and conclude, that they have not received the Spirit, I will take on me to poſe 'em.</p>
            <p>If you had no meaſure or work of the Sanctifying Spirit;</p>
            <p n="1">1. How is it that you daily groan (being burdened) under the weight of ſin, even the body of ſin which you bear about, and that with reſpect to the diſhonour that thereby redounds to God?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24.</note> Dare you deny that it is thus with you?
<note place="margin">Gravia haud gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitant ſuo loco.</note> Or however your great deſire is that it may be ſo; and can you affirm that ſin is ſo heavy
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:154105:49"/>in its own Element, an unſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Soul?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whence is it that you ſee ſuch a ſurpaſſing raviſhing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency in Chriſt Jeſus? That when you are not able to ſay, Your Beloved is yours, and you are his; yet you can ſay, You had rather have an Intereſt in him than a thouſand Worlds? Is he not a Pearl in your Eyes? A very None-ſuch?
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7.</note> Not onely as making Peace for you, but withall as bringing Power for ſubduing ſin, and carrying on Gods Service to you.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Could you (as you feel you do) in ſome degree pant after Holineſs and Pureneſs in your Spirits? Do you not Watch as well as Pray againſt Spiritual de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filements?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3.</note> Are not your Souls for Spiritualneſs in Worſhip? Would you not have Faith and Love to influence the Duties you engage in?</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:154105:49"/>
            <p>Tell me (if you can) where thoſe Hypocrites dwell, in whom the three qualifications laſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med meet?</p>
            <p>As for Profane Perſons,
<note place="margin">Procul hinc procul ite.</note> I may ſay to 'em, ſtand off, ſtand off: From this word which I have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to theſe to whom it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; and hearken to me, that God may hearken to you: The next word is very much for you.</p>
            <p>For the Second branch of the firſt Uſe is as followeth.</p>
            <p>They that are at a want of the Holy Spirit, may hence learn to whom (or whither) they ſhould go for him. Should they not bow their knees, and with 'em their Hearts, to the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and cry, Pour, O pour of this Holy Water thy Spirit upon us?</p>
            <p>I ſhould have more hope that this Uſe would be more uſeful to you, if once you well underſtand your own caſe and ſtate. I may deal with you further about it
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:154105:50"/>ere long; at preſent I propound theſe Queſtions to you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How can you think having the Spirit conſiſtent with ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent ſervice as the Fleſh or the World have from you?</p>
            <p n="2">2. How can you pretend to be inſpired with the Spirit, that have not a great care to demean your ſelves well towards the Spirit, and a fear to reſiſt, yea, to quench or grieve him?</p>
            <p>And O that you would give this a ſerious thought! Can you with confidence look God in the face, or hope to eſcape his dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful wrath if his Spirit be not in you? Could I ſee (or hear of) right relentings in your Hearts for your miſcarriages, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the Spirit, and breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in 'em, that he may breath in you, yea and be a Guide and Governour to you; how joyfully and ſeriouſly would I commend you to (and commend to you) the Grace of God the Father,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:154105:50"/>encouraging you to expect this great gift.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Do not earthly Fathers (even evil ones) know how to give good gifts to their Children?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13.</note> Will not the beſt of Fathers, the Heavenly one, give the Spirit to humble askers?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Grace, though long ſlighted,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 15. <hi>per totum.</hi>
               </note> hath long Arms, and hath 'em open to receive poor Praying Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">Qui dedit gratiam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderii, da hit gratiam deſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam.</note> Will not he that cauſeth Perſons to deſire his Spirit (if they follow on deſiring) anſwer their deſire?</p>
            <p>Seeing upon the Fathers giving the Spirit to Perſons, both he and his Son will be Honoured by 'em; and for his Sons ſake he doth with his Honour give him.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Uſe for Reproof: The firſt branch of the Reproof falls full upon them to whom the Holy Spirit, and the effuſion (or pouring out) of his Grace is matter of Drollery and ſcorn.
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:154105:51"/>It is known, that the men of <hi>Rome</hi> call Proteſtants in ſcorn <hi>Spiritiſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Brownſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery.</hi>
               </note> for their ſpeaking much and honourably of the Aids of the Spirit. May this Spirit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and convince 'em of this ſinful ſin! May they feel his hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling work, that ſo they may not fall under his deſtroying Hand!
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.31, 32.</note> Are not all the Perſons in the Godhead wronged, when the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is ſo? Will not Arrows ſhot at Heaven fall down on their Heads that ſhoot 'em? It is a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation that any are ſo da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Branch is for (or if you will againſt) thoſe that make vain pretenſions to the Holy Spirit, and his differencing work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, when indeed they are too much ſtrangers both to him and them. O that they who caſt off all (or at leaſt moſt of) the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of Chriſt, did not cry up themſelves as men who have moſt of the Spirit!</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:154105:51"/>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 4.23, 24. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Doth Worſhipping God in the Spirit exclude external Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, pointed at in the <hi>Greek</hi> word?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Doth the Spirit ſpeaking in the Heart contradict his ſpeech in the Scripture?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Doth Baptiſm by the Holy Ghoſt ſhut out Baptiſm by Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</p>
            <p>Doth drinking of (or into) the ſpirit,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13.</note> make againſt drinking the Sacramental Cup, that is ſet out by that very Phraſe? Should not Spiritual Perſons uſe and prize Spiritual Ordinances?</p>
            <p>The Third Branch of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof falls to their ſhare, with whom the Spirit of God and his Gracious Influences are at an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue. They neither have, nor deſire to have him. Alas! Alas! is not this evidently their caſe?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Who are ſenſual,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jude</hi> 19.</note> living in Carnal Pleaſures, being given up to 'em.</p>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:154105:52"/>
            <p n="2">2. Who are inſpired with the ſpirit of the World;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12.</note> Earth, Earth, Earth, may be written on their Minds and Affections.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.9. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Who are utter ſtrangers (and that out of choice) to thoſe firſt works of the Spirit, which accompany Salvation, or have it following 'em.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Are they enlightned? Have they a ſight of ſin in its ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? Of Chriſt in his Beauty and Glory? And of Holyneſs in its Excellency and Extent? Is their knowledge near ſo much as a ſpiritual one? Is it any more than a meer literal one? Hath it in it clearneſs of Light,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Doctor</hi> Arrow-ſmith's <hi>Armella.</hi>
               </note> which enables Perſons to diſcern things that differ, or ſweetneſs of taſte for reliſhing what excels?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Are they enlivened? Doth this appear?</p>
            <p n="1">1. By their crying, or breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Prayer after ſpiritual things,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 9.11.</note> and Chriſt, with whom they are given.</p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:154105:52"/>
            <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">Natura principium motus.</note> By their motion in other Holy Duties; and by the vigour and conſtancy as well as freeneſs of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By their ſenſe of what tends to prejudice Spiritual Life. Hath not a little living Child a feeling of a ſmall prick of a pin?</p>
            <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2, 3.</note> By their deſire of proper Food and Nouriſhment, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly of the ſincere (and unmix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) Milk of Gods Word, that they may grow thereby.</p>
            <p>Have they an inward concern about theſe things? O that there were ſuch an Heart in 'em!</p>
            <p>May the Lord ſet this uſe of Reproof home upon thoſe to whom it of right belongs!</p>
            <p n="1">1. Shall ſlighters of (or meer pretenders to) the Holy Spirit be able to ſtand in Judgment? ſurely they will not. What then will be the end of thoſe that take the ſcorners Chair, and play not onely with ſacred things, but alſo with this moſt ſacred Perſon,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:154105:53"/>except Repentance reach their Hearts?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Will not this (to thoſe that hearken to him) ſweet Friend, be found by thoſe that abuſe and undervalue him, a moſt ſevere Foe? Can Perſons during this ſtate endure the terrors he ſtrikes into their Conſciences? How then will they be able to bear his ſtrokes to and in Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity? May he (whilſt Life laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) change 'em thoroughly.</p>
            <p>The Third Uſe is of or for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</p>
            <p>The firſt branch thereof is more large and general.</p>
            <p>Be we all ſtirred up to put this matter upon a fair iſſue and tryal. Is the Spirit poured out on us? Have we received the Spirit which is of God, yea, is God?</p>
            <p>I will (firſt) preſent ſome Conſiderations tending to excite us to this Trying, and to ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in it.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:154105:53"/>
            <p>The firſt is, Many truſt very fooliſhly in truſting their own Hearts,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.26.</note> which Naturally are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true, and as far from goodneſs as from Truth. There were of Old thoſe called <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> and <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniſts,</hi> who called themſelves Spiritual ones, but very falſly; and at this day many ſtrongly conceit, that the Spirit of God is in 'em; but put 'em on proving it, and you ſilence 'em.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There are in all of us (conſidered in our Naturals) Principles that lead us to a vain confidence, that we are Rich,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9.</note> and increaſed with Goods and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.31.</note> And is it not a leading work of the Holy Spirit to ſhew us our ſelf-emptineſs, and bring us to ſelf-loathing?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Is it not of ſad ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification when we decline all ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſearch and tryal in the caſe?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.2. &amp; 139. <hi>laſt.</hi>
               </note> Did not the Man after Gods own Heart ſhew what he was, by his deſiring God to examine and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:154105:54"/>prove him? Were not thoſe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins far out,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.</note> that looked not into their Veſſels, to ſee what ſupply there was in 'em for their Lamps?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, God will to the quick try us. He may ſend on us ſuch a ſudden and ſharp Affliction as will anſwer the name of a Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or Tryal. He will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly come to us by Death,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. <hi>laſt.</hi>
               </note> and bring us to Judgment; and then there will be a full and impartial deciſion of the matter. <hi>Then the Secrets of all hearts will be laid open.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, marks (or ſigns) lye next us.</p>
            <p>And the firſt I ſhall name (which I ſhall do little more than name) having before given an hint of 'em,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Doctor</hi> Manton, <hi>&amp;c. diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd.</hi>
               </note> are excluſive ones: If they be upon Perſons, they are void of the ſpirit of Holineſs.</p>
            <p>To wit, 1. Walking after the Fleſh, and fulfilling its Luſts. Hath the Fleſh a full dominion
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:154105:54"/>within the Spirits Territories?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1.</note> Have they the Spirit whom the Fleſh at a beck can command into its Obedience,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.16.</note> ſo that they will run into exceſs, and be drunk, unclean, or lazy?</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, Living in an ordinary and wilful neglect of Spiritual Duties, or however of Spiritual Graces in the uſe of 'em. Doth not the Spirit of Life (where he enters) bring his Law into the Heart?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2.</note> And doth not Mens Cloſets and Houſes ſavour of it?</p>
            <p>I next come to give ſome of thoſe Marks which are good, but not concluſive.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They may not have the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Sanctification who have had ſome of thoſe preparatory works (as they are called) which Saints have.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 24.25.</note> They may have frights for wrath, that want fear of ſin. They may have ſorrows that have not Godly ſorrow. They may be ſhaken, that are not
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:154105:55"/>ſettled on the Rock of Ages.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They may be deſtitute of the Sanctifying Spirit, that have ſome deſirable motions (and affections) from him. They may deſire benefit by Chriſt, that have no real deſire of Chriſt himſelf: They may deſire him as a Bridge, on (and over) which they paſs to Happineſs, that do not deſire him as an Husband, in whoſe Boſom they may iye, and whoſe Orders they may obſerve. They may love the Loaves, that do not love the Perſon of Chriſt; they may joy in ſome Gifts from him, that count not abiding with him joyful.</p>
            <p>And ſo I proceed to lay down</p>
            <p>Marks ſtyled incluſive. They that carry 'em have received (if not a double) a larger portion of the Spirit, than ſundry others who yet have received him. May thoſe who will vouchſafe to read 'em, deſire that they may bear 'em.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:154105:55"/>
            <p>The firſt is, An hearty and deep deteſtation of inward and thought-defilements, added to an eſcaping the groſs Pollutions of the World.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.113, 128.</note> Though <hi>David</hi> fell far and foully, yet, in his main courſe (and bent) he had an habitual (yea, and actual) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, as of every falſe way, ſo of every vain thought; and therein ſtood above many whoſe Feet are on Holy Ground. An eminent preſence of the Spirit was with him.</p>
            <p>The Second is, A readineſs in many caſes to deny ones ſelf, and part with ones own Right (and concern) not onely for Peace ſake, but chiefly for God's ſake.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.8.</note> Was not Father <hi>Abraham</hi> higher by the Head than moſt are that are his Seed, who not onely yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Lot</hi> that was his Nephew, but alſo refus'd to touch any of the Spoils that were recovered in War, being firſt taken from the <hi>Sodomites?</hi> I know <hi>Balaam</hi> could
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:154105:56"/>ſpeak words of ſelf-denyal, as if an Houſe-full of Gold was as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to him, but it was becauſe God made it too hot for him to hold;
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15.</note> for in his Heart he loved the Wages of Unrighteouſneſs. If a Perſon come to this,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A meipſo libera me, cry'd</hi> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> that he fears the encroachment of ſelf-ends, and is free to be taken off from ſelf-willedneſs, and is Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified as to ſelf-advancement, a large meaſure of the Spirit is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on him.</p>
            <p>A Third is, Walking more evenly and uniformly than moſt do, who yet are in the Road to Heaven.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.24. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> No doubt there were in <hi>Enoch</hi>'s Age other upright Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, yet on account of his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhining 'em, and out-going 'em in Obedience, he hath this High Character, <hi>That he walked with God.</hi> When a Perſon's Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, as to the ſeveral turnings that are in it, are honeſt, and becoming the Goſpel, and is ſo much all of a well-wrought piece
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:154105:56"/>that it is not eaſie for a Friend to find any thing that deſerves a ſharp Reproof,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the Life of Sir</hi> Nat. Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardiſton. <hi>and of the Lady</hi> Wharton.</note> or a Foe to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel with, any practice as incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with ſaving Grace, a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is verily filled with the Spirit.</p>
            <p n="4">4. So is he that gives great Glory to God by exerciſing Faith in the face of many and great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements, was not this an Evidence that <hi>Abraham</hi> was fuller than many of the Holy Ghoſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.19, 20.</note> in that he conſidered not his own Body, being then dead (as to the hope of begetting an <hi>Iſaac,</hi> a Son of Laughter) nor yet the dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Sarahs</hi> Womb? He did not ſo conſider either of 'em, as not to rely on God for fulfilling his Promiſe in giving him Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: He believed in hope againſt hope, he ſet one God over againſt all Objections: His Faith remov'd Mountains out of his ſight.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They have the Spirit above many that are mighty in Prayer; that can humbly and earneſtly
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:154105:57"/>plead in Prayer,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.1.</note> filling their mouths with Arguments, giving God no reſt, till he give in Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals to 'em, and look down on his <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with favour,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.3.</note> being of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s genuine Seed, that Wreſtled till he prevailed,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.24, 28.</note> and would not part with God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Bleſſing.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Spirit alſo ſhews that he is eminently with (and in) thoſe who being beſet with Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, hold up, and hold out, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering ground and ſtrength, and loſing nothing in the fire ſave their droſs: Was it not thus with <hi>Joſeph,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.23, 24.</note> whoſe Bow abode ſtrong when the Archers ſhot at him?</p>
            <p n="7">7. They alſo are above many acted by the Spirit,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.32. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.2.</note> who have a more than ordinary command over their Spirits and Paſſions; and are for ſhewing all meekneſs to all men, and that when not a few,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 12.3.</note> nor thoſe ſmall provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are given 'em. Was it not thus with <hi>Moſes</hi> the Man of God
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:154105:57"/>who in his ordinary temper was to Temptations to Wrath, as moiſt wet Wood is to ſparks, that quencheth, and is not kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by 'em.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The Holy Spirit doth emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently reſide in (and influence) them who can ſtand in as faſt Friends at the Throne of Grace, for thoſe by whom their Earthly Glory hath been eclipſed, and thoſe by whom they have been oppoſed and deſerted. Thus was it with <hi>Samuel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.1. &amp; 12.23.</note> that interceded ſo earneſtly for <hi>Saul</hi> and the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. So have they, who when they have acted (yea, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered) above many for God, do ſtill ſet the Crown and Honour, as did Laborious Patient <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10.</note> on the Head of Free Grace.</p>
            <p n="10">10. So alſo is it with them who are deſirous to ſerve God as they are capable on Earth, yet love the coming of Chriſt; and becauſe they cannot get ſo near
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:154105:58"/>to him as they would whilſt they live,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</note> are deſirous to dye, that they may be nearer him.</p>
            <p n="11">11. This is alſo the choice, caſe, and ſtate of thoſe who highly eſteem God's Ordinances; and yet if (to their ſorrow) they be deprived of 'em, they can live upon the Lord, as a little (or great) Sanctuary.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.25, 26.</note> May thoſe good Perſons, who cannot reach thoſe greater meaſures mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, be reaching after 'em! And may none Bleſs themſelves in their Hearts (or ſtate) till they have on (and in) 'em thoſe marks or ſigns of their having the Spirit, which go under the name of adequate and even; which all the Sanctified, and none but they, have.</p>
            <p n="1">1. One whereof being led by the Spirit out of the love and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of ſin, and out of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in ſelf-righteouſneſs and ſelf-ſtrength, unto the Lord Jeſus, for himſelf, and for Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:154105:58"/>and ſtrength from him.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 15.5.</note> There is no Hypocrite that is for abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in Chriſt; and there is no weak Chriſtian that dare abide out of him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another is, longing to find the workings of the Spirit more full and powerful. They who have known the gift of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 4.10.</note> are for asking larger draughts of the Water of Life. Hypocrites ſet ſtints and limits to themſelves as to things of the Spirit: A little ſerves their turn, and uſually they ſtudy
<note n="*" place="margin">Minimum quod ſic.</note> what is the very leaſt and loweſt degree in Grace, as reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to ſit down there; whereas weak Chriſtians, though they may attain leſs, breath after more, and have a real Spiritual Thirſt on 'em.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Third is,
<note place="margin">Spiritus es tres deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catiſſima.</note> Having a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der reſpect to the moſt tender Spirit of God, and an Holy care (and fear) leſt injury be offered him, and he be as much as by men he can be grieved by inward, and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:154105:59"/>not onely outward miſcarriages. Hypocrites are daring and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking; not trembling, leſt the Spirits motions be quenched, and his Graces lye unexerciſed; and weak Chriſtians accounting the Spirit their Friend, are (in their ordinary courſe) loath to diſpleaſe him.</p>
            <p>The Second Branch of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation hath a particular reſpect to thoſe who upon tryal do (or may) find that they have not the Spirit, as to any ſpecial Intereſt in, and influence from him.</p>
            <p>Be they exhorted to wait in God's way, that he would pour out of the Spirit on 'em.</p>
            <p>Under this Head will fitly fall ſeveral Directions; the Lord di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect 'em to their Hearts to whom they belong.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is, Be they willing to ſee that the Spirit of Grace is not in 'em. Till their wants ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, a ſupply will not be ſought.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9 12.</note> The whole feel not their need of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:154105:59"/>a Phyſician, and ſo will not make out to and for him.</p>
            <p>Beſides what I have offered for their Conviction before, I deſire they would thus poſe themſelves.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Do they ſtudy to ſhew forth the Vertues of Chriſt? Who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived not the Spirit by meaſure,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.</note> from whom all his receive a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Spirit.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 1.14, 16.</note> Is it in their Aims to be Humble, Meek, Pure, Compaſſionate, Active, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly as he was?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Have they warm Hearts for ſuch as are (and appear) Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual? Do they Love their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety in Spiritual Exerciſes? Do they not rather ſeek occaſions againſt 'em,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1.</note> and take up evil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of 'em, and interpret their real weakneſſes to be manifeſt Wickedneſs?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Is Spiritual Worſhip (and Spiritualneſs in Worſhip) prized and panted after by 'em?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3.</note> Do they any thing like Worſhipping God in the Spirit?</p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:154105:60"/>
            <p>O that they that have not the Spirit had their Eyes opened, and that ſtate diſcover'd to 'em!</p>
            <p>The Second Direction is, When once they feel their want of the Spirit, they ſhould ſee what a miſerable caſe that is, and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble leſt they live and die in it.</p>
            <p>Whilſt they live.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Can they carry on the death of any one ſin?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13.</note> Will ſin dye of it ſelf? Or by any Wounds ſave thoſe which the Holy Spirit makes and gives?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Can they expect that any Service in which he breaths not will be ſweet and acceptable to God?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.23, 24.</note> Doth he not ſeek ſuch to Worſhip him as do it in Spirit?</p>
            <p>When they dye (if they dye as now they live)</p>
            <p n="1">1. Have they either Title to, or meetneſs for Heaven?
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.14.</note> Doth not the Spirit fill all the Veſſels of Mercy and Glory? Could they deſire to ſtay in Heaven, if they had admittance into it, who want the Spirit of Glory?</p>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:154105:60"/>
            <p n="2">2. Is not wrath their Portion? Will not the Spirit for ever fill thoſe with Confuſion, that made void all his ſtrivings with 'em in order to their Converſion? Will he not be a terrifying Spirit where he hath not been a Sanctifying Spirit?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29.</note> And will not wrath lye heavieſt on thoſe that have made the greateſt reſiſtance to him?</p>
            <p>The Third Direction is, When a due ſenſe (and fear) as to their preſent ſtate is on 'em; cry they in the name of Chriſt unto God the Father,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 14.16.</note> that the Son may pray down, and the Father toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him may pour down the Spirit on 'em.</p>
            <p>Do they this, 1. Humbly and ſelf-judgingly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.10.</note> in that they are as far as any can be from Meriting one bleſſed ſprinkling or drop thereof. Are they not below the loweſt Mercy?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Earneſtly and thirſtingly: May they who have been as the dry, be as the opening Ground!
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:154105:61"/>May they be taught to Plead as well as Pray: O that the Teacher of Hearts may be their Teacher! May he put into their Mouths ſuch Arguments as follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Lord! the Promiſe of the Spirit is the grand Promiſe of the New Teſtament; we are caſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that diſpenſation; let us reap the Fruit of that Promiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Lord! As thy Spirit is a free Spirit, ſo the Promiſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is a free Promiſe. It is made to the unworthy, and to needers. Now, into that count we fall.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Lord! if we have the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and Communication of the Spirit, thou wilt have much Glory thereby; we ſhall then Crucifie ſin, carry on thy ſervice, and exerciſe Grace; for thy Names ſake give thy Spirit to us.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Lord! though we do not deſerve thy Spirit, we are ſure we deſire him; and we hope we do ſo, that we may be fitter for the work thou aſſigneſt us. We
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:154105:61"/>have this deſire from thy Grace; from it let us have our deſire ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Lord! Thy Providence did order that we ſhould come under the Baptiſm which is by Water; when we had not a value for that Priviledge, we were on the ſcore (and preſenting) of our Parents received into thy Church; will not thy Grace confer on us the Baptiſm of the Spirit, when we are brought to value it? And with our Perſons to preſent our Petitions for it to thee.</p>
            <p>But methinks I hear ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced drooping ſouls ſay, You would have us Pray (and Plead) for the Spirit; how can we do this without the Spirit?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By a more common and general aſſiſtance of the Spirit; you may Pray for his ſpecial In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence.</p>
            <p>It may by ſuch be further Objected,</p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:154105:62"/>
            <p>Though there be a Promiſe of the pouring out of the Spirit, we dare make no claim to it: The Promiſes are made in Chriſt, and made good to thoſe that are in him; but we fear we are out of him.</p>
            <p>To ſuch I ſay,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd. <hi>Mr.</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> There have been (and are) choice Divines, who have held forth, that there are ablolute as well as conditional Promiſes. To be ſure there are Promiſes of Grace, as well as Promiſes to Grace; and troubled Perſons, that dare not claim a Title to the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26.</note> may deſire an Intereſt in the former.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> How, <hi>of Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
               </note> So Rich is Divine Grace, that as an acute Writer writes, Unpromiſed Mercies flow on every ſide us; and Hope built on rational Probabilities, is well cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the great Engine that moves the World, and ſhould move the Objectors to pray for the ſpirit.</p>
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:154105:62"/>
            <p n="3">3. They that dare not apply to themſelves the Promiſe of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.2. <hi>Soles au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire,</hi> Pool <hi>ad locum.</hi>
               </note> conſidering the goodneſs of his Nature, and withall the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences thereof in his diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to Praying ones, have great encouragement to pray for his ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Can it be thought that any have ſtrong breakings, and uſe earneſt crys for the ſpirit, in whom there is not ſome ſpecial working of his?</p>
            <p>It may be, ſome will ſtill Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject againſt themſelves, they have grieved, quenched, and reſiſted the ſpirit; is there any hope they ſhould be made partakers of him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Their caſe, if truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented, calls for deep Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation; yet on their being hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, deſperation muſt be watch'd againſt: Yet this free ſpirit is free to viſit thoſe that have carryed untowardly towards him.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:154105:63"/>
            <p>May ſuch Perſons ſpread before the Lord their great Neceſſity, and his great Bounty! And when they moſt labour under a ſenſe of their own unworthineſs, make they mention of the All-worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Jeſus Chriſt: On this fair and broad bottom they may ſtand.</p>
            <p>O that they were loath to be driven away from the beautiful Gate of Mercy, or to be ſaid Nay! what hope would their caſe have in it?</p>
            <p>The Third branch of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation hath a ſpecial reſpect to thoſe who have a ſpecial Intereſt in the Holy Spirit, and know what it is to have him poured out on 'em.</p>
            <p>Be they excited to wait for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and fuller effuſions thereof on their own ſouls. Have they felt bleſſed drops, they ſhould deſire to experience what floods and ſhowers are.</p>
            <p>Motives thereunto.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hath not God the Father the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:154105:63"/>yea, the fulneſs of the Spirits Graces and Influences to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate? Is there not enough and enough under his Hand?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is he not as free as can be wiſhed to fill thoſe that are ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of their defects?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.10.</note> Hath he not bidden them open their mouths wide?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Did not the Spouſe of Chriſt (joyn'd to him by the Spirit) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that the North-wind might awake,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 4. <hi>laſt. See</hi> Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham <hi>on the place. Rev.</hi> 22.17.</note> and the South-wind blow on her Garden? Which expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are expreſſive of the various Influences of the Holy Spirit? Would not the Bride have Chriſt to come with further diſplays of his Spirit to her?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Do not all the knowing know, that larger meaſures of the Spirit are neceſſary? Have they not Corruptions to ſubdue, Temptations to reſiſt, Duties to perform, and Graces to exerciſe? None of which can be done fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the Spirit helps their
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 26.</note>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:154105:64"/>infirmities, or
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Hollingſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth <hi>from the Word.</hi>
               </note> lifts up over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 'em.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Is it not clear, that a large portion of the Spirit is as excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent as neceſſary? Is it not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to Rivers of living, yea, to the beſt Wine?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Will not this difference 'em from Hypocrites? Are any of that number willing the hand of the Spirit ſhould be on their ſpecial ſin? Or do they deſire the Spirit may work in 'em Graces of all ſorts?</p>
            <p>To wit, 1. Rooting Graces; Humility, and Self-denyal.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Raiſing Graces; Faith, Hope, Love, and Joy.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Spreading Graces; Charity to all, and loving-kindneſs to Saints.</p>
            <p>Means for 'em now come.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Wait they for further Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications of the Spirit in the low way of ſelf-ſearching, and ſelf-abaſing;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.17.</note> having a particular ſenſe of their wants and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:154105:64"/>Are not the low Valleys uſually Richeſt, and beſt laden with Corn?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Get they into the clean way of watchfulneſs. Be they duly afraid of obſtructing and ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Paſſages through which God the Father uſeth to convey the Grace of the Spirit; which may be done,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Through the thick clay of Earth, by letting their Hearts lye too near it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Through the foul Mud of any baſe Luſts (or inordinate appetite) by ſuffering it to enter into,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.1.</note> and ſtay in their Hearts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Keep they in the High-way of Praiſes, for that communication of the ſpirit that is made to 'em.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 67. <hi>latter end.</hi>
               </note> Are not their Hearts moſt meet to receive more when they are moſt enlarged in Thankſgivings for what they have received?</p>
            <p>Have they not matter and ground for high Praiſes?</p>
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:154105:65"/>
            <p n="1">1. Doth not the Holy Spirit dwell in 'em? And doth not that imply,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he is very inwardly preſent with and near to 'em;
<note place="margin">Intimior intimo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro.</note> He is nearer to their Souls than they are to their Bodies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he abides with 'em. There is a fixedneſs and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in his Preſence. He that knocks at the Doors of others Hearts,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend</hi> Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſs <hi>on</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>Pulſat aliorum corda. Dr.</hi> Sibbs.</note> makes theirs his Houſe and Temple. He that moves others at times, will not remove from them, but ſtay with 'em for ever.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That he exerciſeth towards 'em much of Familiarity and Condeſcendence. He uſeth 'em as his ſpecial Friends, as thoſe of his Family; they know ſuch Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitations of his as others are ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Will not the Holy Spirit work where he dwells, and ſo fitly furniſh his Habitation? Will he not be to 'em,</p>
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:154105:65"/>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14.</note> The moſt faithful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductor? Shall they not be led by him?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 14.26.</note> The moſt ſeaſonable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer. Will he not write Truths in 'em?</p>
            <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2, 16.</note> The moſt powerful quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Shall they not have Life abundantly?</p>
            <p n="4">4. The moſt ſatisfying Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Will he not ſpeak to their Hearts?</p>
            <p>Yet in all theſe workings he is a moſt free worker, taking his own way and time.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Be they by no means driven out of the good beaten way of earneſt believing Prayer. On their knees, and through their Saviour, cry they for the effuſion of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>I add, That they may more feel the real effects of the Spirit, beware they of the Rock on which too many are ſplit; to wit, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vain and groundleſs Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to him and his Operations.</p>
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:154105:66"/>
            <p>And ſo in the cloſe of this ſhort Diſcourſe, I will offer at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of ſome Queſtions or Caſes.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is, Are Perſons at this day to look for new Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from the Spirit?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. They are to look that the Spirit would reveal in 'em what he hath in the Scripture re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to 'em;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Vide</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowſmith, <hi>Tact. Sac.</hi>
               </note> but that he ſhould add to the Canon and Rule of Scripture, and make new Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Faith, is not to be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fiſh.</hi> Uſher <hi>Dr.</hi> Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> To ſome choice Favourites that have cleaved to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as to matters of Faith, he hath ſtrongly ſuggeſted what his Providence would do as to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Fact. This he may do to others.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Caſe is,</p>
            <p>Is Duty never to be done ſave when Perſons are under extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary impulſes of the ſpirit to do it?</p>
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:154105:66"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It is brave ſailing before full Gales of this Wind; and ſweet moving when he is ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly the firſt mover.</p>
            <p>Yet, 2.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.17.</note> The Spirit ſpeaking in the Scripture calls us to Pray and perform other Duties, when there is an Opportunity for it; and this Call is to be Anſwered.</p>
            <p>The Third Caſe is,</p>
            <p>Is every impulſe and ſtrong motion to Prayer or other Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to be Father'd on the Holy Spirit?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Hollingſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth. <hi>The late worthy Mr.</hi> Old<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> This is utterly denyed by the beſt Divines. Though Satan (being evil) cannot be the Author of Motions that are purely good; yet he may excite to a work that is for the matter of it good: And if we be moved unſeaſonably and unreaſonably, we may fear his hand is in it.</p>
            <p>The Fourth Caſe is,</p>
            <p>What Uſe are we to make of thoſe extraordinary motions which ſome have had to Actions
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:154105:67"/>in an ordinary way leſs defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; as that of <hi>Phinehas,</hi> and that of <hi>Sampſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We are to think they had full aſſurance thoſe motives came from the Spirit; but our ſelves ſhould tremble, leſt we touch with what we have not a clear word for.</p>
            <p>Now, the good Spirit, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whom theſe Pages are, breath in 'em, and in thoſe that will give 'em a reading. The Lord grant that Writer and Readers may more than ever be filled with the Spirit! <hi>Amen</hi> and <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="part">
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:154105:67"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Fourth Inſtance</hi> OF THE RICHES OF GRACE: TO WIT, <hi>Effectual Calling.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Tim. 1.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And called us—</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>SUch are the difficulties and dangers that attend the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſtianity (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally as to thoſe Profeſſors that are Preachers thereof) that all
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:154105:68"/>encouragements that are given prove few and ſmall enough.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed <hi>Paul,</hi> who found that his Miniſtry drew down and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Totius mundi fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorem. So</hi> Luther <hi>uſed to ſay.</hi>
               </note> the fury of the World up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, being (at the time of his writing) a Priſoner, calls on his Son <hi>Timothy</hi> to fet his face on the Wind and Storms, and hold on in his Holy Warfare; being not onely a Souldier, but a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion-Officer, he ſhould quit himſelf like a good man.</p>
            <p>And to that end, he ſets before him how highly he (with others) was Priviledged by, and thereby engaged to the Lord: In particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, he inſtanceth in his (and their) effectual Calling; and ſo gives us fair footing for</p>
            <p>This Doctrine. <hi>God the Father out of his Free Grace gives Perſons a Powerful Call.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That God the Father is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in the Text, is well argued from his being diſtinguiſhed from Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:154105:68"/>
            <p>And 2. His Calling of Perſons is denyed to have its riſe from their Works, and expreſly affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ariſe from his purpoſe and grace.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Calling of Perſons, ſundry diſtinctions are found; at ſome of which I ſhall point.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad munus foedus. Acts</hi> 17.30.</note> It's either to Office or Grace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is either general; ſo God calls all by the Goſpel to Repent: Or particular, and ſo he calls his own Sheep (and Elect) by Name.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is either outward onely,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 10.3.</note> to the Ear; or inward alſo, to the Heart.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is either extraordinary,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.16 <hi>Acts</hi> 9.4.</note> as <hi>Paul</hi> was called by a voice from Heaven; as was that Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that was bidden
<note n="*" place="margin">Tolle, Lege.</note> 
               <hi>Take and Read;</hi> and directed to the Verſe that turned him: Or ordinary, by the Miniſtry of the Word.</p>
            <pb n="132" facs="tcp:154105:69"/>
            <p n="5">5. It is either ineffectual, or effectual.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex effectu vocationis.</hi> Hoorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. p.</hi> 342.</note> Some are barely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited, others anſwer the invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Some ſo far anſwer the Lord's Call, as to come to the Profeſſion of Chriſt, and external Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with his Members; and ſo are of the Church conſidered as viſible.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> 343.</note> Others ſo anſwer it, as to come to the poſſeſſion of Chriſt, having inward Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with him as their Head; and ſo are of the Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as inviſible.</p>
            <p>My ſhort Treatiſe is to run con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe that are ſo called,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.6.</note> that they are choſen, being <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or <hi>Iſraelites</hi> indeed, and not onely of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now we will enquire what is implyed in the Notion (or Phraſe) of Effectual Calling?</p>
            <p>For Reſolution whereof I ſhall lay down ſome Poſitions.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is, Men in their meer Naturals are afar off from God.
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:154105:69"/>O that they conſidered this!
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12, 13, 14.</note> We do not uſe to call thoſe that are at hand and near us. Though God be nigh to all, as to his Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and Providence; many, and many are far from him, as to their Choice and Affection: They are in the World, without God in the Word;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> they are ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, and ſo in a ſort Atheiſts.</p>
            <p>The Second is, No meer Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane voice, no word of Man can (or will) reach thoſe that are in that ſtate.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.8.</note> They are as unwilling as unable to come in of themſelves; and ſo a ſtrong and loud Call from God is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the caſe. Is there not a ſtone in mens Hearts that may be called (as one we have read of is) the deaf ſtone?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> Heylin.</note>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.4, 5.</note> It renders 'em like the deaf Adder, they hear not Spiritual Charmers.</p>
            <p>The Third is, Though men cannot, God can ſpeak home to the Hearts that are hardeſt of Hearing. Is not his voice at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:154105:70"/>with Power?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29.3, 4.</note> Are not the Spiritually deaf and dead made to hearken to it? As none hath an Arm like Gods,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 5.25.</note> ſo none (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Men or Angels) have a Tongue like his. Was not his Word a Creating Word? And is it not an effectually calling word?</p>
            <p>The Fourth is, When God ſpeaks to perſons powerfully, he ſpeaks to 'em particularly, even to every one of 'em by Name; and doth in effect ſay,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>So ſaid Rouzing</hi> Fenner.</note> 
               <hi>Thou art the Man, Thou art the Woman, with whom I have to do.</hi> Too many put off the Word of God from 'em;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 13.46.</note> and count the great things of his Law a ſtrange thing, or things wherein
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.12. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Septuag.</hi>
               </note> the concern of others lyeth; but thoſe whom God calls in the ſenſe of my Text cannot do ſo, they muſt hear and Anſwer.</p>
            <p>And ſo the Fifth is, Upon this Call perſons come out of their former reſpect to their ſins, and confidence in themſelves, unto
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:154105:70"/>Jeſus Chriſt, that they may be and abide in him. They that have ſitten general calls to them among others, cannot but ſtir when God directs this peculiarly to themſelves.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.5.</note> Doth not Power go forth with the Word, ſo that it is a working Word? <hi>He ſaith to one, Come, and he cometh; to another, Go, and he goeth; and to a third, Do this, and he doeth it:</hi> He ſo calls, that he Converts 'em.</p>
            <p>The Sixth is Ordinarily; this Call is given to Men that ſit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Miniſtry. I deny not the Lords Liberty to go his own way; far be it from me to limit the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael!</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah</hi> 6.9.</note> I grant he makes good uſe of Rods; many have taſted Honey on the end of 'em. But is it not his manner by Rods to cauſe words to be more regarded?
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4, 5.</note> Doth he not love to own and honour his own ſpecial Inſtitutions; and ſpeak by his Embaſſadors, that are as his mouth?</p>
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:154105:71"/>
            <p>If any deſire a further account concerning the Nature of this Call, they may do well to repair to the Catechiſm. On the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription given therein of it, I ſhall give the hints that come next.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Effectual Calling is a Divine work. A work of God on the Creature,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Opus ad extra.</hi>
               </note> and ſo the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divided work of all the Perſons; though (according to my Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine) the Father (or firſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in order of working) is firſt in it.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ordine ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi,</hi> Wolleb.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Clear it is, 1. This work flows from a Power that is Divine: Who ſhort of the Almighty can ſo call as that men ſhall hear and live.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This work hath its riſe from Divine Pity. Who but he that is the God of all Compaſſion would ſo call thoſe that have wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully departed from him, and are prone to do ſo?</p>
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:154105:71"/>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, Firmin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Effectually-called Perſons are convinced Perſons. All that hear of Chriſt are bound to come to him; but none will come ſave thoſe that ſee and feel a need of him.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28.</note> Is the Phyſitian of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in great requeſt with any ſave ſuch as are ſenſible of their Souls Diſeaſes? Doth not he eſpecially invite the weary and heavy laden?</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.16. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> When God calls Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo as to cauſe 'em to hear and come to him, he not onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinceth 'em of ſin, but withal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veals his Son to, yea (and in) 'em.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18.</note> He opens their Eyes whom he turns from the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan to himſelf. Faith is a ſeeing Grace, and ſo is ſtyled Knowledge. Do not they who chooſe Chriſt, ſee the greateſt reaſons for their Choice?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, They that are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my Text Called,
<note place="margin">Velle na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae, bene velle gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, eſt.</note> have a change wrought in their Hearts and Wills. Though there is no
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:154105:72"/>force put on the faculty of wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, there is a bleſſed alteration of the quality of the will.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13.</note> They who ſtill will freely, are enabled ſo to will the beſt good.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.3.</note> Are not People made to choice purpoſes willing in the day of God's Power?</p>
            <p>For the demonſtration of the truth of the Doctrine, I ſhall touch on two plain important Points.</p>
            <p>The Firſt Point is, God doth give ſundry perſons an Effectual Call: Who can make a doubt of this, that well obſerves thoſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects that are as ſo many Eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of it?</p>
            <p>To wit, 1. Mens leaving, yea, loathing thoſe ſins they once ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly loved; yea, being moſt ſet againſt ill ways they were moſt ſet on.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Mens being for the denying (yea,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26, 31.</note> dethroning) of that ſelf, which was once their Idol; ſo that they who loved themſelves
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:154105:72"/>more than God, would onely love themſelves in reference to God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Chriſt who was out of mens Hearts is higheſt in 'em.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10.</note> He in whom they ſaw no Beauty, is in their Eyes the chiefeſt of ten thouſands.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7.</note> They greatly prize him, when they cannot clearly prove their Intereſt in him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Holineſs and ſtrictneſs which they formerly declined, is made their way.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.4.</note> They chooſe the things that pleaſe God; and are grieved for their ſhort failings as to following him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The ſetting forth the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God (which before they ſlighted) is now much in their Aims and Deſigns.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Second Point is, They who are Called, owe their Being ſo to God's Free Grace.</p>
            <p>This will be evident,</p>
            <p n="1">1. If we conſider 'em abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Are they not utterly unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy thereof? Were they not moſt
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:154105:73"/>worthy to have been paſt by; yea,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.</note> caſt off? Were they not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together born in ſin? And have they not in the courſe of their Lives acted ſuitably to the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of their Natures? Is not this manifeſt to their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces?</p>
            <p n="2">2. If we compare 'em with others. Can it be thought that Grace which hath made, did find a difference in 'em,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10, 11.</note> except it found ſundry of 'em in worſe Circumſtances than moſt near 'em? Doth not God ſometimes direct his Call to the chief of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 9.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> Sometimes ſtopping 'em as he did <hi>Saul</hi> in purſuit of their ſins.</p>
            <p>I add,
<note place="margin">Agens li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berrimum.</note> Is not God moſt free in all he gives? And ſo in giving this Call?</p>
            <p>May we be taught of God here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to make the beſt Application!</p>
            <p>Firſt inferring, That the Free Grace of God (particularly of God the Father) beſpeaks our
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:154105:73"/>Meditation, yea our Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Do not the Riches of his Grace ſhine upon, if not into, the Eyes of all thoſe that are exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally called by the Word of God? Is not the Goſpel ſtyled Grace,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11.</note> the Grace of God? not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Grace is the Subject on which it treats, but withall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the Spring from which it flows.</p>
            <p>I deny not, that the Creatures are Witneſſes as of the Being, ſo of the Bounty of God; they have a Tongue and Language:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> But Scriptural Revelations have the Advantage, both as to fulneſs and clearneſs. They more ſhew the Face and Heart of God.</p>
            <p>And that the Sun of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in the diſpenſation of the Goſpel ſhould ariſe on ſome when others are benighted and left in the dark. Is not the hand of Grace in this?</p>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:154105:74"/>
            <p>Surely then, 2. The exceeding Riches of Divine Grace are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played on behalf of thoſe to (and in) whom the Call of God is inward and effectual.</p>
            <p>Doth not this appear on a right reſolving of ſome Queſtions?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Were they not chargeable, not onely with diſtance from and difference with God as they were in their Natural ſtate,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.6.</note> but withall with many and great deviations from and provocations of God in their Practice?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Can they upon their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.2.</note> and anſwering the Call of God, add a mite to his Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Glory? Doth their goodneſs at beſt extend to him?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Was not the ſtate out of which they are called a very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal and doleful one?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.8.</note> And ſo ſet out by the name of Darkneſs,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See Dr.</hi> Manton.</note> which takes in Ignorance, Sin, and Diſcomfort; and implyes their unfitneſs to honour and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy God.</p>
            <pb n="143" facs="tcp:154105:74"/>
            <p n="4">4. Is not the ſtate into which they are called a moſt deſirable one? Is it not ſet out by Light,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.</note> which hath its luſtre? Is not this Light ſtyled marvellous? And that deſervedly.</p>
            <p>Seeing, 1. It reſembles that which appears to thoſe that have been long in the dark being Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It diſcovers things great,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Watſon.</note> and greatly to be admired, even Heavenly Myſteries.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It hath admirable Vertues;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10.</note> being 1. Cleanſing. 2. Healing. 3. Quickning. 4. Hearing.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41.</note> It is the dawning of the Day of Glory, which is full, and will be Eternal; where the Joy is always freſh, and (beyond expreſſion) refreſhing.</p>
            <p>The Second Inference is, The Office and Employment of the Miniſtry is of great Uſefulneſs and Honourableneſs. May all enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged therein conſider this! Are not Miniſters as the Lords Mouth,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:154105:75"/>by whom, as the Goſpel is the voice in which he uſeth to call men? Doth he not create the fruit of the Lips, Power, Power, as well as Peace,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.19.</note> Peace? Doth he not much ſend by theſe Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers? Wooing very many, and winning not a few. Did not one of the Ancients call another of 'em the Parent of his new Life,
<note place="margin">Novae vitae parentem.</note> he being ſo under God; O that at him (through Miniſters) Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers did more look!</p>
            <p>The Third Inference. They who hear the joyful ſound of the Goſpel ſhould hearken diligently thereunto, and wait, that he who therein gives 'em Calls, would therewith give 'em hearing Ears,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3.</note> and underſtanding Hearts.</p>
            <p>I am far from ſaying, that men can give efficacy to Calls given 'em; but I know they may provoke God not to give Efficacy to 'em; and as to thoſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue unconverted,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.4.</note> God will clear himſelf when he Judgeth 'em
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:154105:75"/>for not coming wholly over to Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Was not Chriſt preſented to 'em as an adequate object of Faith?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Were they not urged to come to him by moving Motives, drawn from the ſweeteſt Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſevereſt Threatnings?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Had they not the ſame Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Powers with thoſe that came to him?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Did they (as they ſhould have done) call on and cry to the Lord, that he would give 'em ability and willingneſs, and cauſe 'em to come?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Will it not on a due ſearch be found,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.40.</note> that their unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was the immediate hindrance of their not coming? And that unwillingneſs was cauſed by their being in league with ſome baſe Luſt?</p>
            <p>That Hearers may be more mov'd to hearken to Goſpel-calls,</p>
            <pb n="146" facs="tcp:154105:76"/>
            <p>Be it conſider'd, 1. The Lord is very real in the offers and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of his Grace; and it would highly pleaſe him if ſinners did embrace and accept 'em. Far be it from us to queſtion his Word in the caſe; who yet to give us full meaſure hath added his Oath,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.7. <hi>Vae nobis ſi Deo ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranti haud credamus.</hi>
               </note> and ſworn by his Life (which none can queſtion) will not woe be to thoſe that believe him not when he ſwears?</p>
            <p n="2">2. God calls not ſinners for any need he hath of 'em;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 22.2.</note> Stars might rather profit the Sun, than man be profitable to his Maker.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The way of ſin from which God calls men is diſhonourable to them, and not to him onely; and will, if not turn'd from, damni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie (yea,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.31.</note> damn) 'em for ever.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Obedience he calls to is every way for their good.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah</hi> 6.8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29. <hi>Qui jubet, juvar.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. It will be made eaſie through his Grace; who is ready to qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie the Humble for that which he calls 'em to. May ſinners give
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:154105:76"/>theſe things the weight they deſerve!</p>
            <p>The Fourth Inference. It is the near concern us all to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune with our own Hearts, and make diligent ſearch, whether God from (and by) his Grace hath effectually Called us.</p>
            <p>Motives unto it are, 1. Many have an external Call, who want an effectual one.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They that are Call'd effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. <hi>laſt.</hi>
               </note> may come to know their ſtate. 1. The Rule for Tryal is right. 2. The Spirit is ready to aſſiſt Tryers. 3. They whoſe Evidences are good, have great cauſe to rejoyce. 4.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.2. <hi>See on this my dear Brother</hi> New-come's <hi>Sinners hope.</hi>
               </note> If on Tryal the Caſe of Perſons be not found good, there is a Cure in (and for) it.</p>
            <p>May great heed be taken that the Standard be ſet even and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeably to Scripture, and neither too high nor too low, that ſo we may take a true meaſure of our ſelves.</p>
            <pb n="148" facs="tcp:154105:77"/>
            <p>For our furtherance therein, I ſhall on this Subject, as I did on a former, lay down</p>
            <p>Marks excluſive. If they be on us, we are not called accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God's purpoſe and grace.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is, Being in love with darkneſs, and ſo with the ſleep it inclines to;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 3.19 <hi>Joh</hi> 21.14</note> O how many avoid Knowledge, and affect Security!</p>
            <p>The Second is, Driving a trade and courſe of Profaneneſs, being Creatures of carnal pleaſures.</p>
            <p>The Third is, Minding, ſavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Animalia voluptatis.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and reliſhing Earthly things, mainly, if not onely. Eating duſt is that the Serpent is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd to; far unfit is that Food for the Seed of the Woman.</p>
            <p>The Fourth is,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10.</note> Having an aking Tooth and envious Heart at the better ſort of People.</p>
            <p>The Fifth is, Setting light by God's Word, and being void of the love of the Truth.</p>
            <p>I proceed to inſtance in marks that are good, but</p>
            <pb n="149" facs="tcp:154105:77"/>
            <p>Not Concluſive. Sundry have 'em, who have not been Effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Called.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is, Eſcaping ſome of the more groſs pollutions of the World.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Fowler.</note> Men may be without open Crimes, and yet without Chriſt.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11.</note> If we believe the boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Phariſee,</hi> he was no Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, or Oppreſſor.</p>
            <p>The Second is, Being (at times) found in ſome Duties (for the matter of 'em) commendable.</p>
            <p>Such. as, 1. Hearing the beſt Miniſters;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 6.20.</note> 
               <hi>Herod</hi> ſate under <hi>John Baptiſt</hi>'s Teachings.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Praying in publick and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate: Hypocrites have made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and long Prayers.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Obſerving ſome Faſt-days:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58 2, 3.</note> Had not the <hi>Phariſee</hi> two in a week?</p>
            <p>The Third is,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11.</note> Being entruſted with and intereſted in choice Church-Priviledges.</p>
            <p>Such as, 1. Being joyn'd in and to a good Society. Were
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:154105:78"/>not fooliſh Virgins with the wiſe?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Being waſhed with the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Baptiſm:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 8.</note> Was not <hi>Simon Magus</hi> ſo?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Being admitted to the Holy Table:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.26. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Gratias gratis da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras.</hi>
               </note> The bare Plea of eating and drinking in Chriſt's preſence will be found inſufficient.</p>
            <p>The Fourth is, Attaining Gifts that are deſirable, and to others Edifying.</p>
            <p>Such as, 1. Being able and apt to enlarge in Prayer on ſundry occaſions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Prophecying in Chriſt's Name,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.14. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.20, 21, 22.</note> or Preaching very plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly.</p>
            <p>I add, The Unconverted may, 1. Seem Zealous for the Sabbath. 2. Declare for Reformation. 3.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 42.4, 5. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.24.</note> Come to Miniſters with Caſes. 4. Beg a ſhare in their Prayers.</p>
            <p>Now we come to marks</p>
            <p>Incluſive. They on (and in) whom they are, are without doubt called to be Saints: And it may
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:154105:78"/>paſs for an adequate (or even ſign) of ſuch a Calling, if Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons do earneſtly deſire and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to bear and expreſs 'em. Such deſires and endeavours weak Chriſtians are acquainted with; and the furtheſt reaching Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites ſtrangers to. May there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Readers be careful in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering 'em! And full of longings that they may have more and more experience of 'em!</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt is more general; to wit, having a new Heart, or Principle of Spiritual Life and Love.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</note> This is (as one ſaid) the great crack found in many Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels that are found in God's Houſe (or Church) conſider'd as viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>latter end.</hi>
               </note> They build without regard to a good Foundation; and bear, without reference to the root of the matter. Some Fruit they have; but about having the Seed of God they are not concern'd: They are ſeen moving in ſome Holy Duties, but never felt
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:154105:79"/>breathings after that Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from whence ſuch motion ſhould flow.</p>
            <p>Many are chain'd and not chang'd; or have onely known a change of their ſins, and not of their Souls; they do not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a thorough change.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That their Underſtandings may not onely diſcern between good and evil,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17.</note> but alſo between good and good; the good that may ſerve 'em, and that which can ſatisfie 'em.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That their wills may be ſet againſt ſin, and for (and on) God. Where a renewing work is, Effectual Calling hath certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been; about which we may have better Information from the following</p>
            <p>Particular Signs. The firſt is, Brokenneſs and Poverty of Spirit. If we ſpeak of perſons of Years,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.3.</note> hath not that Heart been broken that is ſound? Is Converſion there, where Contrition hath
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:154105:79"/>never been? They who can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that they are not onely hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, but humble;
<note place="margin">Non ſolùm humilitati, ſed humiles.</note> broken in a good degree for ſin, from ſin, and from their former ſelf-confidence; who, as they know they are vaſtly indebted to Divine Juſtice, they feel they have nothing wherewith to pay, and are undone, if Chriſt appear not as their Surety; who have a quick ſenſe of their want of Sanctifying Grace, and that ſupplies can onely be had with and through him, have an hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful evidence of their being Called.</p>
            <p>A Second is, Cleaving to and glorying in the Lord Jeſus as a None-ſuch for a Mediator and Reconciler of God to man by his merit, and man to
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Herles.</note> God by his Spirit; as Wiſdom for their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, Righteouſneſs for their Juſtification,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.</note> Sanctification as freeing from the Reign of ſin, and Redemption (at laſt) from all ſort of Suffering.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3.</note> Rejoycers in Chriſt are of the Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:154105:80"/>or Spiritually Circumciſed.</p>
            <p>A Third is, Chooſing God in Chriſt as the Treaſure, ſaying from their Hearts, <hi>Whom have we in Heaven but thee?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25.</note> And what is that on Earth that we deſire beſides thee?</hi> Thou art that Sun, whoſe preſence makes a day in our Souls: Thou art All in All in Heaven, and beſt of all on Earth, both in the want and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of Creature-Comforts. Is God liv'd on as their Portion by any that are uncalled?</p>
            <p>A Fourth is, Waiting for the guidance and influences of the Holy Spirit. Art not they the Sons of God that are led by this Conductor?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.25.</note> And living in him, deſire a deſign to walk in and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, longing that he would mortifie their Fleſh, and revive their Spirits?</p>
            <p>The Fifth is, Bending Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Providences (both favouring and frowning) againſt ſin; ſtill ſtriking at the Head and
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:154105:80"/>Heart of it, aiming at its Death,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24.</note> and arguing for it from Mercies and Judgments, and longing that at Sermons it may receive ſome Deaths-wounds. Is it thus with any ſave the Called?</p>
            <p>A Sixth is,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, 6.</note> Having growth and ſtrength of Grace in deſire; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for adding to Faith Vertue, and to Vertue Knowledge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for building up themſelves on the Rock of Ages;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Vide Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ad lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</hi>
               </note> and for ſhewing that Love, Joy, Meekneſs, Long-ſuffering, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are one and the ſame Fruit of the Spirit, and for being every day ſtronger and ſtronger.</p>
            <p>The Seventh is, Having reſpect to all God's Commandments: Not wilfully making balks in ſuch good and holy Ground;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.5, 6. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12. <hi>Biſh.</hi> Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow.</note> but ſtudying to walk Godly, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and Soberly; as one in my Youth gloſs'd on thoſe Adverbs, acting in thoſe good ways from a good Habit, and regarding the manner and end with the matter of Duties.</p>
            <pb n="156" facs="tcp:154105:81"/>
            <p>The Eigth is,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.1, 2, 3.</note> Breathing much after the flouriſhing of <hi>Zion:</hi> For her ſake not being ſilent, but praying that ſhe may have Peace, Peace, freedom from Diviſions within,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.6.</note> and not onely Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from without, that her Children may reſemble their Heavenly Father, and be full of Soul-proſperity.</p>
            <p>The Ninth is, Keeping up a Watch againſt all ſin,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 13. <hi>laſt.</hi>
               </note> and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations thereunto: Carrying in mind that the World is their great Adverſary,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 2.16. <hi>Haec tria pro trino numine mundus habet.</hi>
               </note> and its Profits, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and Honours are the great Baits it lays to enſnare 'em.</p>
            <p>The laſt is, Prizing Heaven as it is a place (and ſeat) of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Holineſs; and accordingly making preparations for it, in exerciſing true, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring for more through Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>I much fear many will truſt, and not try; and too many will be ſlighty in their trying, and
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:154105:81"/>not beg that God would ſearch and try 'em.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>If upon Tryal, weaker Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians do find any one ſure mark, with a deſire that the reſt may be found on 'em, it is a good ſign. More good Divines than one have ſaid,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Sibbs. <hi>Mr.</hi> Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth.</note> 
               <hi>One right Grape cannot grow on a Thorn.</hi> But let the unſound know their going about to divide between Graces and Duties, is of ill ſignification.</p>
            <p>The Fifth Inference is, They who have not heard the voice of God, nor known what his Calling is, ſhould not reſt in their preſent condition, but call on him whoſe Calls have Power in 'em, to give 'em the Call they have heard and read of.</p>
            <p>Know they, 1. As far as any of 'em are off, he can eaſily make 'em hear.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As vile as any of 'em are,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 5.25. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15.</note> his Grace can fully forgive 'em, and move him to call 'em: Of this <hi>Paul</hi> had full Proof. And
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:154105:82"/>in order to their being ſo Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged,</p>
            <p n="1">1. May they be for ſeating themſelves under a Miniſtry in which there is plainneſs,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21.</note> clearneſs, and ſeriouſneſs; thereby God uſually calls.</p>
            <p n="2">2. May they uſe all earneſtneſs, as thoſe that would not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.2, 3, 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 42.8. <hi>John</hi> 14.16.</note> May they engage the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful to engage in Prayer for 'em.</p>
            <p n="4">4. May they when they dare not ſay they have an Intereſt in Chriſt, Pray that he would take 'em into (and bear 'em on) his Heart, and prevail with his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſpeak ſo to 'em by his Spirit, that they cannot but hear. O that there were ſuch hearts and workings in ſinners!</p>
            <p>The Sixth and laſt Inference is, They that are indeed and in truth the Lord's Called ones,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſhould ſhew forth the Vertues (and thereby the Praiſes) of him that hath called'em.</p>
            <pb n="159" facs="tcp:154105:82"/>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1.</note> Should not their Hearts lead in their Praiſings? Should not all their Powers and Forces be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into this Service? Are they not above others engaged and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled thereunto?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.6.</note> Should not the High Praiſes of God be in their mouths? Should not the Calves of their Lips be offered to God?</p>
            <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.1.</note> Should not their Lives be referred to his Honour?</p>
            <p>That they may be ſo,</p>
            <p>May the Twenty Rules follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be attended to! O that they were more Anſwer'd by em!</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.1, 2, 7. He is <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius oculas.</hi>
               </note> Live they in and under a full and powerful apprehenſion of God's Omniſcience. Is he ſhut up or ſhut out any where? And doth he not ſee their ways and Hearts with whom he is?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">Omne ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num in ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo bono.</note> Maintain they a conſtant dependence on God's All-ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency. Is not all good bound up in the chief good? Cannot he eaſily ſupply all wants,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1.</note> ſupport
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:154105:83"/>under all preſſures, and fit for all Services.</p>
            <p n="3">3. May there be on (and in) 'em abiding and influencing thoughts of the extream evil of ſin!
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Dr.</hi> Goodwin, <hi>&amp;c. Rom.</hi> 7.13.</note> Is it not as truly as uſually ſaid, <hi>A worſe name than its own cannot be given it?</hi> O that it more appear'd in its own ugly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours!</p>
            <p n="4">4. Do they frequently review and reflect on the diſhonour done to God by their ſins paſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.12.</note> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally their heightened ones. Can they fully number or weigh 'em? And ſhould not the ſight of their black feet be very humbling to 'em?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Take they into ſerious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration the ſhortneſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency of their own Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</p>
            <p>As to appeaſing the wrath, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying the Juſtice, and procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the favour of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.7, 8.</note> can Raggs cover 'em? Can defiled Raggs cleanſe 'em?</p>
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:154105:83"/>
            <p n="6">6. Be they much in admiring the Riches of Grace, which hath fully provided for 'em, and the deſign thereof carried on by Chriſt for 'em.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah</hi> 7.19.</note> Is not Gods Grace as the depths of the Sea, which they cannot fathom? And as the heights of Heaven, which they cannot reach? And doth not Grace that brought Chriſt down from Heaven to Earth intend to bring them up from Earth to Heaven?</p>
            <p n="7">7. Keep they as near as near may be to the Bleſſed Jeſus.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20</note> Cloſe they with his Perſon, apply they his Righteouſneſs, and imitate they his Example. May he lye Day and Night between their Breaſts! May they live on him as All and in All!</p>
            <p n="8">8. Prize they the ſpecial Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and wait they for the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Aſſiſtance of the Holy Spirit.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.16.</note> May he more and more inſpire their Souls and Services! May he ſubdue their Corruptions, and
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:154105:84"/>draw out their Graces!</p>
            <p n="9">9. Keep they their Hearts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a deep and endearing ſenſe of God's many great and choice Mercies to 'em. How precious have his thoughts been to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1.</note> Can they know the ſum of 'em? And hath not his hand of Grace in ſundry Inſtances been lifted up high?</p>
            <p n="10">10. Be they for out-ſhooting the Heathens in their own Bow, and out-ſtripping 'em in the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues wherein they excell'd.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Mr.</hi> Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> This hath been ſtyled borrowing the Jewels of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering the Flowers in Natures Garden to deck themſelves with. It's a ſhame that they in and of the Church ſhould be leſs ſober, chaſte,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.</note> or juſt, than ſome our of it.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Study they to be extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, adorning the Doctrine of their Saviour in all things.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.10.</note> May their Beds and Boards, may their Shops and Fields, may their em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:154105:84"/>and refreſhments car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a mark of Holineſs on 'em!
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 14. <hi>laſt.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. Husband they their time (and the ſeaſons of Grace there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in afforded) to the beſt purpoſe and profit.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.15.</note> May they not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly trifle or ſquander away one Golden Hour! but fill up every day with proper Duty.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Be they for making a good uſe of the Word and Works of God. Be they loath to be as leak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or broken Veſſels,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.1. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>See the late Reverend Dr.</hi> Owen <hi>thereon.</hi>
               </note> leſt they take in Errors, or let ſlip Truth. May what God doth as to them or others be conſtrued in a right ſenſe, and improved to a right end, that they may be brought nearer, and made liker to God!</p>
            <p n="14">14. Be they much concerned about the Converſion of Perſons, and preſervation or reſtauration of Goſpel-Order in Churches.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 2.5.</note> May they long that there may be a great Addition to the Church, and a great agreement to Rule of every thing in it!</p>
            <pb n="164" facs="tcp:154105:85"/>
            <p n="15">15. Have they much recourſe to the great and precious Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes? Are they not Breaſts of Conſolation, and Wells of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation?
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> Are not Promiſes as Glaſſes, wherein the Lord's Heart is ſeen, and through which Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders are transformed into his Image, and made partakers of his Holineſs?</p>
            <p n="16">16. May their Actions be free as from Contagion,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Mala co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorata.</hi>
               </note> ſo from ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion! may they ſhun the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of evil, together with apparent evils! may their wall ſavour of an Holy diligence and laboriouſneſs!</p>
            <p n="17">17. May Patience have a more perfect work in 'em!
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>James</hi> 1.2, 3.</note> may they take up, and not onely bear the Croſs of Chriſt! may they have more and better Rule of their Spirits! may they ſhew their ſtrength by their ſtanding under Burdens!</p>
            <p n="18">18. Be they much in contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances what they ſhall render to
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:154105:85"/>God, or how they may moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.12, 13.</note> Let this be one of their Morning ſtudies, that he may have the glory of the Day, and of their daily ſtudies, how he may be magnified by 'em in Life, and in Death.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Look they much above (and before) 'em at Heavens Glory.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20.</note> May their converſation be there whence they expect their Saviour; at their Reward, in the midſt of their Work; at their Crown, under the weight of their Croſs, may their Eyes be.</p>
            <p n="20">20. Joyn they together thoſe gracious diſpoſitions which ſeem to differ. Be they courteous to all, without ſinful complyance with any. Be they Zealous, and yet withall Meek and Diſcreet;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.11.</note> mix they Reverence with their Rejoycing.</p>
            <p>Bleſs they God for Temporals; but themſelves onely in him who is Eternal.</p>
            <pb n="166" facs="tcp:154105:86"/>
            <p>O that theſe Rules were ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſtians as Copies, that they might write after 'em, when they cannot in exactneſs of walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reach 'em!</p>
            <p>Holy are, and Happy ſhall they be, that mourning for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and relying on the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, in whom was no defective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, put and preſs on towards perfection.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.18.</note> Duty lyes at mens doors, but Ability is derived from God's Grace. May this hint, which is often mentioned, be always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred by thoſe whom the Lord hath Called!</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="part">
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:154105:86"/>
            <head>A Fifth Inſtance <hi>OF THE RICHES OF GRACE: TO WIT,</hi> God's Covenanting with Man.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſa. 55.5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And I will make an everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with you.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHO would refuſe him that ſpeaks from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? Eſpecially when he ſpeaks in ſuch melting, moving Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:154105:87"/>as is found in the firſt Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of this Chapter. O what ſweet and Holy Charms doth the Holy Ghoſt here uſe! As a Learned Doctor ſaid on another account,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>O quam ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cro faſcino uſus eſt! Sententia D.</hi> Morto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, <hi>p.</hi> 25.</note> I may ſay on this, <hi>If Eloquence her ſelf had a Tongue, ſhe could not uſe words of greater force.</hi> As many words as there are, ſo many Weapons and ſtrong Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments there are to Conquer and overcome the Oppoſition that is in ſinners Hearts.
<note place="margin">Quot ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba, tot tela.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Here is line upon line, invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon invitation; and that to every one that is a thirſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 1. <hi>Engl. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not.</hi>
               </note> to <hi>Gentiles</hi> as well as <hi>Jews.</hi> All to whoſe Ears theſe Calls ſhall come, are aſſured (as much as truth can aſſure 'em) that if their whole Souls come to and for a whole Saviour, they ſhall have him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 3.</note> and with him Life, even that Life that is moſt worth ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and doth beſt deſerve the name, even length of days for ever and ever.</p>
            <pb n="169" facs="tcp:154105:87"/>
            <p>My Text is counted the laſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Sedg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick <hi>on the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi>
               </note> I am ſure it is not the leaſt Reaſon wherewith the Lord's Call is backed: Upon mens coming in, the Lord will make with 'em a Covenant, and that a Covenant that ſhall not be made void, an everlaſting Covenant.</p>
            <p>Obſerve we, 1. The Promiſer, God; particularly, though not onely the Father. 2. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; which contains,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The thing Promiſed; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king (cutting or ſticking) this Covenant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">Vide Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ad locum.</note> The Subjects Recipient of the benefit of this Promiſe; to wit, ſuch as anſwer the Invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion given, pointed at in the word <hi>You,</hi> whatever you have been for ſinners: Therefore,</p>
            <p>Having thus made our way thereto, we lay down</p>
            <p>The Doctrine. <hi>God the Father out of his Free Rich Grace doth Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with Perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="170" facs="tcp:154105:88"/>
            <p>Of his Covenanting we read often; and if when we read, we do alſo weigh what is written in the Text, will not the fulneſs and richneſs of his Grace be preſented to us? May we not well ſtand a while on every word before us, and proclaim ſuch Grace?</p>
            <p n="1">1. How much is there in the firſt word <hi>I?</hi> Which points out the firſt Founder of the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, the firſt Perſon in the Trinity, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Will God that humbleth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to behold the things that are in Heaven,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.5, 6.</note> vouchſafe to look with favour on Offenders here on Earth? Will he look on man with an Eye of Love, that ſees how he hath loſt and defaced his Image? And that leads me to conſider,</p>
            <p n="2">2. What emphaſis and force there is in the laſt word <hi>You.</hi> In what a plight doth God find thoſe he Covenanteth with?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. <hi>beginning.</hi>
               </note> Will the moſt High condeſcend ſo low as
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:154105:88"/>to deal familiarly with Subjects, yea, with Rebels? What was man in his firſt eſtate, that God ſhould make with him a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Friendſhip? What then is the Son of man,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.6.</note> or man in his fallen ſtate, that God ſhould make with him a Covenant of Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation? Will God indeed make a Second Covenant with him that is chargeable with the wilful vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the firſt?</p>
            <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">See the Ark of the Teſtament opened.</note> Is not God's Covenanting an Act of his Free Rich Grace? All grant, that his Goodneſs (ſome ſay his Grace, though not Goſpel-grace) was ſhew'd in the Covenant of works: God might have exerciſed his Sovereignty in giving <hi>Adam</hi> a Law, without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing his Bounty in promiſing him ſuch a Life upon his obeying it.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Doctor</hi> Bates <hi>his barmony. Rom.</hi> 5.7.8.</note> His Covenanting with man put an Honour on him, and in rendring his Obedience more free, rendred it more firm: What ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and favour then is it to man,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:154105:89"/>that is in his Blood, that in a Covenant-way God ſaith to him, <hi>Live?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Doth not the Property of this Covenant (to wit, its being everlaſting) advance mans Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge by it, and conſequently God's Grace in it? This Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was everlaſting, as to the Foundation of it, which was laid in the Covenant of Redemption, and will be everlaſting, as to the benefit, giving men a Title to, and at laſt poſſeſſion of perfect unending Salvation.</p>
            <p>Who that gives the things touched on, the thoughts due to 'em, ſees not cauſe for that joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſound, <hi>Grace! Grace!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And being to treat on that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which is according to its name (in an eminent way) the Covenant of Grace, my Text treating thereon; and having made ſome mention of two other Covenants, I ſhall preſent ſome Poſitions that preſent ſomething
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:154105:89"/>of its Nature, and of its diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend</hi> Bulk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley <hi>on the Covenant. Iſa.</hi> 58.10. <hi>See Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend</hi> Blake.</note> This Covenant is made with Man, and ſo differs from the Covenant of Suretyſhip that was made with Chriſt for men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Covenant is made in order to man's Reſtauration; and ſo differs from the firſt Covenant that was made in order to man's Confirmation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Covenant runs much in a Promiſing way and ſtrain:
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39.</note> It's called the Promiſe, and is a bundle of Promiſes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Grand Promiſe in it is,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Summa foederis. Gen.</hi> 17.7.</note> That God will be his Peoples God. This is ſaid to be the ſum and ſubſtance of the Covenant.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 3.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16.</note> Faith is required in and of thoſe that are ſo in the Covenant, as to be entituled to the Pardon and Salvation promiſed in it.</p>
            <p>I am aware,
<note place="margin">Camero de foedere, &amp;c.</note> that in the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of great Divines, we read of an abſolute Covenant; and the Covenant we are on is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:154105:90"/>to that of <hi>Noah</hi> (or made with <hi>Noah</hi>) after the Flood, which was of that kind.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.9.</note> God will no more deſtroy the Earth by Water, though its Inhabitants be not well qualified; and hereupon excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent men expreſs themſelves ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what differently.</p>
            <p>Some are leſs free to hear of a condition in the Covenant, when others are full for its being Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional.</p>
            <p>I had rather (if I were able) make up ſeeming breaches, than attempt to make 'em wider, and accordingly ſhall Note,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That they who ſay it is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional, do not mean, that any thing found in man was the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of God's making it;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8.</note> or that Faith call'd the Condition of it is of a mans ſelf; ſo that he ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther works it, or deſerves that God ſhould do it; or that where it is wrought, it merits what is given into its hand.</p>
            <pb n="175" facs="tcp:154105:90"/>
            <p>And not a few of 'em ſay,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Jeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop. <hi>M.</hi> Baines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> that it is a Condition in the Covenant, or a conſequent Condition flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the Covenant, and conveyed through the Miniſtry of it.</p>
            <p>Others of 'em ſay, it is from what we call the Covenant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as a Teſtament,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret.</note> or how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever from the Covenant made with Chriſt, he having a Promiſe that it ſhall be wrought in thoſe that are given him.</p>
            <p>So that all they intend by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting the Conditionality of the Covenant is,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 3. <hi>laſt.</hi>
               </note> that without ſuch a Faith as calls Repentance and Obedience Daughters, none that are of years have a right to Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and Glorification.</p>
            <p>They obſerve, that the current of the Scripture is for joyning Faith and Salvation, Repentance and Remiſſion: And the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is ſpoken of as a Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Covenant; and ſo implyes a conſent in thoſe that come within
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:154105:91"/>it to the terms and tenor of it: And hence it becomes a more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and full Covenant, having God and Man for Parties.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, The moſt valuable among thoſe that are leſs affected to the term, condition in this caſe, grant,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God obſerveth an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Method in conferring Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-benefits;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Capel <hi>M. Trough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton. Mr.</hi> Gale, <hi>&amp;c. Mark</hi> 16.15, 16.</note> ſo that men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Grace for (and on) Grace; one bleſſing depending on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and none of Age ſhall be ſaved but believing Penitents.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Covenant of Grace doth directly require Faith as a means of accepting and applying it;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>So Mr.</hi> Though<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</note> and it doth alſo require Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and Obedience conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentially, as Qualifications ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to fit the ſubject to receive what Faith apprehends in the Promiſe.</p>
            <p>And may it not be thought that according to theſe conceſſions, Faith (yea, and in a ſort Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance)
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:154105:91"/>do put on the Nature of conditions,
<note place="margin">Induere naturam conditionis.</note> and that the thing is owned, though the word be not.</p>
            <p>And now I that am not ſo good at definitions as to give you one of mine own of the Covenant, ſhall take that of another.</p>
            <p>The Covenant of Grace is a new Compact (or Agreement) which God hath made with ſinful man,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>So Mr.</hi> Sedgwick.</note> out of his meer Mercy and Grace, wherein he Promiſeth that he will be our God, and we ſhall be his People; and undertakes to give everlaſting Life, and all that conduceth thereunto, to all that believe in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And having given ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that as we do not gainſay ſuch as ſay that the New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant (if we reſpect the Spirit of it, and the intention of its Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor) takes in a purpoſe to give to many Grace that will iſſue in Glory; ſo they do not oppoſe our aſſertion, that in the external
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:154105:92"/>form and propoſal of it, it is of a conditional Nature.</p>
            <p>We will go on with an Eye to what we find in the Context to ſet down,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">Vide Dick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoni Thera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peudica Sac.</note> The Condition or Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of ſuch as are willing to come into Covenant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That which is moſt ſtrictly the Condition of the Covenant.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That which is ſtyled the Condition of Covenanters.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt, None will hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily conſent to the terms of the Covenant but ſuch who are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1.</note> and have a Spiritual thirſt on 'em.</p>
            <p>In (and unto) which thirſt there are three Ingredients.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A ſenſe of Soul wants. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the reſemblance holds between the thirſt of the Body, and that of the Soul. A thirſty man needs no one to tell him he wants what is moiſt, cooling, and quenching, his feeling tells him this to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. After this manner it is
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:154105:92"/>with him that thirſteth after Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.17.</note> and the Father's Grace in him: He feels a want of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, Peace, and Power.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This ſenſe of wants is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with pain and uneaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs till a ſupply be had.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 19.28.</note> It is well known, natural thirſt is not well ſuffer'd or ſufferable: Even our Bleſſed Lord cry'd out, <hi>I thirſt.</hi> Thus it is with the thirſters under conſideration; they can no more well bear the want of Water of Life, than thirſters that of other Water.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thence ariſeth a very earneſt deſire of Refreſhing. Give a man that is athirſt Gold or Pearles, if you give him not ſomewhat to drink, he is unſatisfied. Tell him you'l give him drink hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that will not ſerve his turn,
<note place="margin">Quantum pro quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillo?</note> he would have it at preſent. What would not a man in extream thirſt give to be quenched? It's ſtoried, one gave a Kingdom, and then cryed, <hi>How much have I parted
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:154105:93"/>with for a little?</hi> Suitably hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they that are Spiritually athirſt would very fain ſhare in the Riches of Grace; they would have Grace juſt now, they are willing to have it in God's way: Others cry,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>So Mr.</hi> Caſe.</note> Give us grace when we dye; their cry is, Give us grace, or elſe we dye.</p>
            <p>As to the Second, The Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Covenant in greateſt ſtrictneſs is true, ſound, unſeigned Faith, which hath ever Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance waiting on it. This in the Contex is ſet out under the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Buying; which word muſt not be ſet on the Rack. If a proper meritorious price be ſpoken of, Faith hath no hand in, pays no penies towards ſuch a price. The Commodities are ſo Rich,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>So Doctor</hi> Arrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith.</note> and the Chapman ſo Poor, there is no room for Bartering: Is not Faith as an empty ſelf-emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tying hand?</p>
            <p>But as he who buyeth, parts with ſomething, and comes up
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:154105:93"/>to terms: So he that believeth, parts with former love to ſin, and truſt in his own Righteouſneſs and Strength, and is at one,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.45, 46.</note> ſo he may have Chriſt, he'l not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer terms of his own, but accept thoſe of Chriſt, and be thankful for 'em. As is well obſerved, Faith is alſo ſet out in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text by coming to him, and eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and feeding on him: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſome careleſs Wretches will not ſo much (or if you will,
<note place="margin">Idem.</note> ſo little) as come to the Waters or Ordinances; ſome that come, do meerly come; they do not chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, or ſeriouſly enquire how they may partake of what is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered. Others come and cheapen, and bid fair, but they will not come up to the Market; they have ſome ſin which they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to have: And as to eating, feeding, and living on the Lord Jeſus, they are ſtrangers.</p>
            <p>As to the Third, The Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Qualification required and
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:154105:94"/>found in ſuch as have ſincerely Covenanted, is uniform or uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Obedience; a thing of great Excellence,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond. <hi>See his Life. Iſa.</hi> 55.3.</note> commended as the one thing by a late Learned Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. This is pointed at in and by hearkening diligently to the Lord, inclining the Ear to him, and hearing, that the Soul may live. Holy and happy are they whoſe Obedience is ſuch as to their hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty purpoſe and endeavour, who do truly, and would throughly experience what cloſe walking with God is.</p>
            <p>And now it is time to prove that Grace is written in great Letters on God's Covenanting with fallen Man.</p>
            <p>And beſides what hath been hinted about that, I Argue,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In general, Is it not Grace in its greatneſs, that God hath Intereſted Perſons in what he is? How big with Mercy is his womb? Will not God the Father be the Father,
<note place="margin">Quantus, quantus eſt?</note> and God the Son the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:154105:94"/>and God the Holy Ghoſt the Comforter of Covenanters? Is not God's wiſdom theirs for their Direction?
<note place="margin">Deus meus &amp; omnia.</note> His Power for their Protection? And his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for their Proviſion? What would they have, or would they wiſh, that's not bound up in this word, <hi>I will be your God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>More particularly, 1. Will not God iſſue (and grant) out to his Covenant-People the free and full Pardon of their ſins?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.8, 9, 10, 11.</note> Though it be true, they did the Facts, and were therein in fault, and did deſerve wrath; yet that guilt which would bind 'em over to eternal Puniſhment is taken off and away.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1. <hi>Oculo vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice.</hi>
               </note> Are not their Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions covered, ſo that God ſees 'em not with an imputing Eye? Surely forgiveneſs is ſuch a prime Bleſſing,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.32. <hi>See</hi> Pool <hi>on it.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Moſes</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving uſed theſe words, <hi>If thou wilt forgive their ſin,</hi> there ſtops; hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that they who have that Mercy, want none that is ſaving.
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:154105:95"/>O what eaſe have Souls when this Mountain is mov'd!</p>
            <p n="2">2. Will not God alſo ſubdue the ſins, and carry on his work of Sanctification in Covenanters? Shall ſin have dominion over them who are under Grace?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14.</note> And will not God be writing his Law in a fairer Character in their Hearts? So that their Hearts ſhall more agree with it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. <hi>See Doctor</hi> Preſton <hi>on the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. Litera ſcripta ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net.</hi>
               </note> as the Copy doth with the Original Deed; and this ſuitableneſs ſhall abide, as Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings do: Will not the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new their ſtrength, and ſtrengthen the bruiſed Reed?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Will not God vouchſafe a gracious hearing acceptance and anſwer to their Prayers? When Holy <hi>Micah</hi> had ſaid,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah</hi> 7.7.</note> 
               <hi>My God,</hi> he might well add, <hi>will hear me.</hi> Are not the liſpings of little Children pleaſing to Parents? We that hear the crys of others Babes, can feel thoſe of our own. But what is our tenderneſs to Gods? Will he not give us a return to their Suits
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:154105:95"/>what they want,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> though not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways what they wiſh? Are not his Ears unto their crys as
<note n="*" place="margin">Mr. Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</note> one gloſs'd on it, laid cloſe to 'em? Are not their whiſperings and chatterings (as his Spouſes voice) pleaſant to him?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Will he not take in good part their other Services? Will he not pardon what is theirs, and accept what is his own in 'em? Doth not Chriſt eat his Honey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb with his Honey (as one ſaith) take cruſt and crum to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Mr.</hi> Trap.</note> when preſented by his Spouſe.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12.</note> Where there is a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling mind, works leſs perfect paſs. When Sacrifices are offered on the Altar, and go through Chriſt's hand, they are well taken.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Will not God put a peculiar reliſh on the good things they have? Have they not his Bleſſing,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.3, 4, 5.</note> which adds no ſorrow, but much ſweetneſs to enjoyments? Are they not Bleſſed within doors and without? Is not that the moſt
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:154105:96"/>delicious Bread that is taken out of the Ark of the Covenant? Do not lower Mercies flow to Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters from the upper Spring, the Heart as well as the Hand of God?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Will not God Sanctifie and ſweeten their Sufferings, and turn evil things into good to 'em? Shall not the Rods they are whip'd with be like <hi>Aaron</hi>'s bloſſoming ones?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.</note> Shall not croſs and cold Winds blow them gain? Shall not Meat come out of the eater, and Honey out of the Rock of hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips unto their Souls? Shall they not ſcape the Curſe, when they bear the Croſs?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>So Biſhop</hi> Sander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33. <hi>laſt.</hi>
               </note> Doth not God give 'em Correction with the ſame Hand wherewith he hath given 'em Chriſt? Will not Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (yea, Death) be altered as to them?</p>
            <p n="7">7. Will not the Lord in the time of Life make 'em Bleſſings?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.2.</note> Doth not that Bleſſing of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> (even the Promiſe of being
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:154105:96"/>as having a Bleſſing) come on the Believing <hi>Gentiles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14.</note> who are his Seed according to the Faith? What though they be Women, and ſo of the weaker Sex; yea, Servant-Maids, and ſo of the lower Rank, will not God make 'em uſeful and inſtruments of good,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5.3.</note> by their Prayers and Paterns, if not otherwiſe?</p>
            <p n="8">8. Will not God when he takes 'em from the Earth, take their ſeparate Souls into Glory?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.32.</note> Hath not he engaged to be their God? And ſhall Death break that bond? And are not they whoſe God he is as to their better part,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Doctor</hi> Templar. <hi>Idea, p.</hi> 312</note> as are <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> (at this preſent) living, to (and with) God? Have they not good ground for their ſaying, who ſay, that by that time their Friends have well cloſed the Eyes of their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> their Spirits ſhall be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to behold God's Face in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs? Shall they not imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately on their departure be with Chriſt?</p>
            <pb n="188" facs="tcp:154105:97"/>
            <p n="9">9. Shall not their Bodies, on which Death ſeizeth, be raiſed out of the Duſt, that in their whole Perſons they may be Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py to (and in) Eternity? Hath not our Saviour left it under his hand,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 6.39</note> that he will loſe nothing, not onely no Soul, but nothing, no Body that is given him? Are not the Bodies of Covenanters the Purchaſe of his Blood, and Temples or Habitations of his Spirit?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>M.</hi> Jeanes <hi>Scholaſt. Div. p.</hi> 28, 29.</note> He is not the God of the dead of thoſe, any part of whom ſhall dye for ever.</p>
            <p>Surely what I have written proves the Covenant to be of Grace. May my Reader go to the Labours of that Dear Brother on this Subject,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> H. Newcome <hi>on the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi>
               </note> whoſe Tongue and Pen God hath eminently Bleſſed.</p>
            <p>And now muſt I go to ſome brief, may it be bleſſed!</p>
            <p>Application. And the firſt Uſe ſhall be by way of Caution.</p>
            <pb n="189" facs="tcp:154105:97"/>
            <p>Take we heed leſt from the Doctrine of God's Covenanting with Man, we conclude that this his Covenant doth in all points anſwer thoſe Covenants that are amongſt (and between) Men: Surely this Covenant doth far and far tranſcend 'em.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Hath any Humane Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant ſo much of freedom in it as God's hath?</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the Ark of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened. Job</hi> 22.2, 3.</note> Do not Men in their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants propound ſomething of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to themſelves? This can have no place in God, whom no Perſons or Praiſes can in the leaſt profit; his glorious name being above 'em.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Do not men ordinarily ſee ſomething of worth and loveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in thoſe whom they take into Covenants of Friendſhip and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity? But what of worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or lovelineſs is there to be ſeen in fallen Man?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.1, 2, 3, &amp;c.</note> Is he not in his blood and gore, in his filth and guilt? And yet that is made a time of Love.</p>
            <pb n="190" facs="tcp:154105:98"/>
            <p>Secondly, In what meer Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Covenant is there ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion, as is expreſſed in this Covenant? If a Prince ſhould ſtoop to make a League with a Peaſant,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.5, 6. <hi>Finiti ad infinitum nulla pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portio.</hi>
               </note> yet he that is ſo far a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove as to Office, is but an equal as to Nature. But between the Creator and Creatures what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion is there?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, What lower Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is like this high one in firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſureneſs? Have not men like men tranſgreſſed and varied? And on Mens part,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.7. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13 5. <hi>Sal eſt du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raturae amicitiae ſymbolum. Iſa.</hi> 55.4.</note> in this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant there are too many failures; but as to the Lord, it is a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Salt, laſting and incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible. Do not the ſure Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of <hi>David</hi> belong to this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>Jehovah changeth not; therefore the Sons of</hi> Jacob <hi>are not conſumed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Is it not eminently to mans Honour, yea and to God's, that God thus Covenanted?</p>
            <pb n="191" facs="tcp:154105:98"/>
            <p n="1">1. Though men may Bleſs others,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144. <hi>laſt.</hi>
               </note> are not they the Bleſſed of the Lord, whoſe God he is in a Covenant-way? Is not this a Covenant of Life?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Are not God's Attributes as evidently ſo joyntly diſplayed herein? Infinite Wiſdom hath ordered a meeting of Mercy and Truth, of Righteouſneſs and Peace; Juſtice receives ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Grace is in its exaltation; ſin is condemn'd, and ſinners ſav'd; the Law fulfilled as to the Surety, and the Goſpel advanced; as to thoſe for whom he is ſo.</p>
            <p>The Second Uſe is for Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
            <p>The firſt Branch is, One ſtep or conſideration is before us, on which we ſhould ſtand, and afreſh wonder at Divine Grace.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.3, 4, 5.</note> Are not the People a People of Grace, to whom the Covenant belongs as to its external and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Adminiſtration? Were not the <hi>Jews</hi> in this reſpect known
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:154105:99"/>(and honoured) above all the Nations of the Earth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.6.</note> being to God as peculiars, and a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure?</p>
            <p n="2">2. When Perſons are inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Covenant, and have a right to its choice benefits, can we take a meaſure of God's Grace to 'em? What but that could move him to Covenant with them? On their laying hold on this Covenant, and Union to the Mediator there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3, 4.</note> the Covenant of works can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not demand any thing of 'em, which Chriſt and his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will not anſwer. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they ſtand chargeable with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring God's Juſtice and Holineſs,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Herle's <hi>Tripes.</hi>
               </note> the former will be righted through the ſatisfying Merit of Chriſt; and reſpects paid to the latter through his Sanctifying Spirit; by his Purchaſe they ſhall be freed from the damning power of ſin, and by his Power from the reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Dominion of it.</p>
            <pb n="193" facs="tcp:154105:99"/>
            <p>The ſecond Branch of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Uſe is, They are inexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble who ſtand off from Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting with God, and will by no means be prevailed with to come within this bleſſed Bond,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2, 3.</note> though the Lord ſay, <hi>Ho every one, Come, come, come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Many turn the deaf Ear on him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.</note> and will not come within the hearing of Wiſdom's calls, that cry loud (as one Phras'd it) till ſhe be hoarſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Many are Hearers onely;
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10.</note> they open the outward Door of the Ear, but keep the inner one of the Heart ſhut.</p>
            <p>They are led unto Truth, but not into it; they receive it not in its light and love; or if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in ſome light, it is but for a ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>May not many Preachers ſay,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.1.</note> 
               <hi>Who</hi> (comparatively) <hi>believeth our Report?</hi> Few are as the good Ground, that had depth of Earth, and moiſture enough. Few have
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:154105:100"/>been ſteep'd in ſorrow, or are in that ſtream carried to receive a whole Chriſt, and reſign them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to him. Few from a right underſtanding of the tenor of the Covenant with Hearts and Hands ſubſcribe to it. I will ſay to Recuſants,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>Come and let us rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Have you not been too too long ſinfully coy, forſaking your own Mercy?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Can you poſſibly be happy, if you be not in a Marriage-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with the Lord?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Can you ſtand under the wrath that is over rejecters of the Covenant?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. <hi>laſt.</hi>
               </note> Is not a little (a very ſpark) of this fire ſcorching? Can your hands be ſtrong, or your hearts endure in the day of God's ſharp viſitation? Might not Chaff ſooner endure the Wind,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.14.</note> and Stubble the Fire?</p>
            <p n="4">4. What will you Plead why wrath ſhould not have its free courſe on you?</p>
            <pb n="195" facs="tcp:154105:100"/>
            <p n="1">1. Was not cloſing in with the Covenant your Intereſt as well as Duty?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Did not the Holy Spirit ſtrive with you,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28.</note> and perſuade you to do it?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Were you not ſometimes under convictions and good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations?</p>
            <p>Firſt, Will you offer to ſay, Covenanting with God is more than needeth?</p>
            <p>I ſay, 1. Let Scripture be judge of that: Do not its Precepts en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn it? Its Promiſes encourage it? And its Paterns lead to it?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Have you not done it Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentally? Is it any more than Baptiſm binds to?</p>
            <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45. <hi>latter end.</hi> &amp; 56.5, 6.</note> Will not this at Death and Judgment appear one thing neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Will you not be undone for ever, if this be not done? What will it avail you, that the Church is your Mother, if God in a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-way be not your Father?
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:154105:101"/>Will not all your external per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> S. Shaw.</note> yea, and your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions to glory in Chriſt's Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, be conſtrued as an Eſſay to bribe the Lord, that he fall not on you, whilſt you reſolve not to be his through and through?</p>
            <p>Secondly, Will you ſay, you are not yet at leiſure to attend this buſineſs?</p>
            <p>I will ſay, 1. What then have you leiſure for? Or for what end is further ſpace given you? Is it not in order to your Repentance? In which Covenanting with God is included.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Do thoſe employments or enjoyments with which your time is taken up ſatisfie you?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.21.</note> Have not the faireſt Roſes that grow in Natures Garden prickles about 'em?</p>
            <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.27.</note> Shall you not at Death be ſent to thoſe Comforts you ſo doted on in the time of Life, that you neglect God? Will they not then be burdens to you?</p>
            <pb n="197" facs="tcp:154105:101"/>
            <p>Thirdly, Will you ſay, It is a Summers day to Night; hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you'l Covenant with God?</p>
            <p>I will ſay, 1. In whoſe Hand is your time? Is it not in his you ſtand off from? Cannot he ſoon end it?</p>
            <p n="2">2. If your time continue, may not ſeaſons and ſtrivings of Grace ceaſe? This Tide may be the laſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.15.</note> You ſpeak as Perſons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concern'd in the Honour of God: If you were ſure he would accept your laſt fruits,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33.</note> ſhould you not out of choice give him your firſt-fruits? Is the beſt you have good enough for him?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Do you plead, you have otherwiſe diſpoſed of your ſelves? You are in Covenant with ſome ſin, and will not be ſo with God.</p>
            <p>The Reply is ready: 1. This is plain dealing; but are you not aſhamed on't?</p>
            <pb n="198" facs="tcp:154105:102"/>
            <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">Quo War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranto?</note> By what Right did you give away your Hearts? Are they not by right the Lords?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Your diſpoſal is illegal, and ſo void
<note n="*" place="margin">Ipſo facto</note> in and on your doing it?</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Obligation to Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting with God is on you; may you through grace anſwer it!</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Do you ſay, you have Covenanted with God?</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, That is very good, if very true. Attend you well to what will be next offered you.</p>
            <p>The Third Uſe is for Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The firſt Branch is general. Be we all excited to look (and long) that there may be on (and in) us ſuch Characters as will be Proofs that our Covenanting with God is ſincere.</p>
            <p n="1">1. May we clearly apprehend, and highly eſteem the juſt and honourable terms required in (and of) thoſe that do ſo Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant!
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:154105:102"/>to wit, ſin-diſliking,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 24.7.</note> ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſclaiming, and Saviour-accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. May our Hearts ſay, Theſe terms we like!</p>
            <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. &amp; 11.28.</note> May we inwardly (and daily) grieve for Original ſin; and for this branch of it, averſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to cloſe with Goſpel-tenders, and to glorifie Chriſt, to which his Spirit leads!</p>
            <p n="3">3. May we when in ſecret (and ſeriouſneſs) much admire that Rich Grace that founded the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and hath been ſet before it!</p>
            <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 6.44.</note> May we feel a need of ſpecial Grace to bring into and keep in this Bond! May we be ſenſible, that the Fathers drawings brought us to, and the Spirits Influences hold us in Chriſt!</p>
            <p n="5">5. May we find this Bond for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible on us, reſtraining us from ſin when tempted to it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining us to Duty when prone to decline it! Do we ſay to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, we have made a Dedication
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:154105:103"/>of our ſelves to the Lord; his Vows are on us, how can we ſlight him?</p>
            <p n="6">6. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.6, 7. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5.</note> Do we from this Covenant fetch our ſupports under down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtings in diſtreſſes and upon the apprehenſions of Death. Holy was <hi>David,</hi> that ſaw and went this good way.</p>
            <p>O that all Readers Souls breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after ſuch Expereinces!</p>
            <p>The Second branch is more particular, They who have not engaged their Hearts to approach to God, ſhould be at unreſt till it be done. To them</p>
            <p>The Firſt Direction is, Get they a good Underſtanding of thoſe great Points of Divinity that are related to the Covenant.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 24.7.</note> Doth not God give thoſe with whom he Covenants an Heart to know him? Is not Covenanting an Act of the Intelligent?</p>
            <p>O that all were clear as to theſe Heads!</p>
            <pb n="201" facs="tcp:154105:103"/>
            <p n="1">1. Man cannot have Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God, except God greatly condeſcend.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That God Covenants with him, is a great condeſcenſion (and honour) to Man.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That Man broke the firſt Covenant was very ſinful, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſs was with undutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Every Child coming from <hi>Adam</hi> (in the ordinary way) by that breach is a Child of wrath.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It's no ſmall part of the Curſe on man, that he ſeels not his ſtate, nor deſires a change of it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Except the Covenant-ſtate of Perſons be chang'd, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand in Judgment.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It's the wonder of Angels, God will tranſact with men in a new way.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The New Covenant is made in (and through) a Mediator.</p>
            <p n="9">9. This Mediator (Chriſt) is a compleat one; being God-man,
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:154105:104"/>a Prieſt to God, and a Prophet and King to men; obtaining, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring, and applying Salvation.</p>
            <p n="10">10. To the Mediation of the Son, the Miniſtration of the Spirit is graciouſly added.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That Perſons may have benefit by Chriſt, they muſt be joyned and married to him.</p>
            <p n="12">12. None will conſent to Chriſt till convinced they abſolutely need him.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Grace that joyns to Chriſt doth ſtill aid thoſe that are in him.</p>
            <p n="14">14. All that are in Chriſt are for dying to ſin, and living to Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p n="15">15. They who partake of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-grace ſhall partake of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-glory; and together with underſtanding theſe Points, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhould underſtand concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Action of Covenanting.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it is a free Action: Being a Marriage-covenant, choice is requiſite.</p>
            <pb n="203" facs="tcp:154105:104"/>
            <p n="2">2. It is a deliberate Action, grounded on the ſtrongeſt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is a Reſolute Act: A Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanter is to be againſt revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his Choice.</p>
            <p>The Second Direction is, Feel they (as well as ſee) a neceſſity of Covenanting; both that of Precept,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Praecepti medii.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30 7. <hi>Data ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.12.</note> and that of means as to attaining Heaven. Yield they themſelves, give they their Hands (and Hearts) to him. He that hath not the Son, ſo as to Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with the Father through him, hath not Life; he hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther right to, nor fitneſs for it.</p>
            <p>The Third Direction. Be they for a ſpeedy and thorough breach of Covenant with ſin:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>So Mr.</hi> Gibbons.</note> That Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally Men are in this unholy League is a kind of ſenſible thing. That it ſhould be diſſolv'd is a needful thing.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21.</note> Men cannot at once be in their ſins and their Saviour.</p>
            <pb n="204" facs="tcp:154105:105"/>
            <p>The Fourth Direction. Time is to be ſet apart, that this work may be well done.</p>
            <p>To wit, 1. In and with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamenting frame;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.3, 4.</note> weeping that it was not done ſooner.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In a ſelf-judging frame; owning that wrath was their due, and that they have neither ſtrength by which they ſhould cloſe with the Lord,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5, 6.</note> nor worth for which he ſhould help 'em to do it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In a Praying and Pleading frame; waiting that God for Chriſt's All-worthineſs would perſuade their Hearts to enter his Covenant.</p>
            <p>Plead they thus: 1. Lord! thy Grace offers thy Son; will it not teach us to embrace him?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Lord! It is our Duty to Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with thee; wilt thou not enable us to do it?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Lord! On Covenanting with thee, we ſhall Honour thee; help me to Honour thee.</p>
            <pb n="205" facs="tcp:154105:105"/>
            <p>Some doubting drooping Souls may Object againſt themſelves:</p>
            <p>Firſt, We are ſo very vile, God will not accept us if we give our ſelves to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 6.37. &amp; 7.37.</note> Satan and your miſ-giving Hearts may ſay ſo; but where did God tell you ſo?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hath not be plainly told, that on your coming, <hi>he'l in no wiſe caſt you out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. To multiply Pardons to the Penitent, is for his Honour: Be willing he ſhould have Honour.</p>
            <p>A Second Objection. We have dealt falſly as to our Baptiſmal Covenant; can we hope God will deal with us after his gracious Covenant?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.12, 13. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.1, 21, 23.</note> Great Humiliation is called for; Deſperation is a Rock to be avoided.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Covenanting with God (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding paſt Treachery) is ſtill your Duty.</p>
            <p>A Third Objection. We fear, if we do make Covenant, we ſhall break it.</p>
            <pb n="206" facs="tcp:154105:106"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thry <hi>on a Chriſtians great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1.</note> It being your Duty, fear muſt cauſe you to do it aright, but muſt not hinder your doing it. When in your ſelves you are without ſtrength, have recourſe to the Spring of ſtrengthning Grace. It is ſufficient for, wait that it may be effectual in you.</p>
            <p>The laſt branch of the Exhortation, is for thoſe that with a right hand and heart have laid hold on God's Covenant.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Walk they as Covenanters ſhould do.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.3. and 119.6.</note> May they exerciſe Obedience! that is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Free; and out of Choice, being Voluntiers in God's Service.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Extenſive; reaching every part and point of the Law, as to their will and purpoſe.</p>
            <p>They ſhould have reſpect to inward and Inſtituted Worſhip; to the right manner and ſpecial time of Worſhip; to the exerciſe of Religion in all their Relations; to the maintaining of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 13.22. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Purity, Juſtice, and Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and that their Obedience may hold on and out to the end.</p>
            <p>Secondly, May their Faith be in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant exerciſe! May they always hold the Bleſſed Head,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20.</note> the Lord Jeſus! May the Life they live in the fleſh be by the
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:154105:106"/>Faith of the Son of God! Are not all their freſh Springs in him who is called the Covenant? May they go out of themſelves as empty, poor, and weak; unto him as full, rich, and ſtrong be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond expreſſion? Is not this the Spirit of the New Covenant?</p>
            <p>Again, That the former Direction may be better obſerved, let this that follows take due place.</p>
            <p>Be they for a frequent and ſerious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newal of their Covenant.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Strong <hi>on the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, p.</hi> 184, &amp;c.</note> Freſh Cords may have much force. Do not many, and many find it good for them in this way to draw near to God?</p>
            <p n="1">1. After freſh falls and declinings,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 22.31.</note> in order to their riſing and recovery.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Under great preſſures and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenings, in order to their ſupport and chearing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the time of quicknings and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largings,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.4, 5.</note> for the prevention of dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſtraitneſs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Before great Enterprizes and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, that they may be Bleſs'd and Proſper'd.</p>
            <p n="5">5. At the cloſe of Sabbaths and Faſts,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9. <hi>latter end.</hi>
               </note> that precious impreſſions may be abiding; yet great care muſt be had, leſt Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity eat out the Heart of this Practice; and in new Covenantings, new Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:154105:107"/>from Heaven are to be waited for.</p>
            <p>The laſt Uſe is for Conſolation to thoſe who have ſuffered (and do im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove) the foregoing words of Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.22. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the word ſignifies both.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5. <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>May they not with joy draw Water out of this Well of Salvation?</p>
            <p>Is not God's Covenant an everlaſting one, well order'd in all things, and ſure? Is not this one branch of it, that he will never, never, never leave or forſake thoſe whom he cauſeth by it to cleave to him? Will he ſuffer 'em fully and finally to depart from him? Shall bewailed failures in Covenant be taken as forfeitures of it? Aſſuredly they ſhall not.</p>
            <p>May this poor Piece have Heavens Bleſſing attending it! And may by all that read it Covenant Mercies (in the uſe of Covenant-duties) be received! <hi>Amen</hi> and <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:154105:107"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
